<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Mat Goebel MD MAS NR-P</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Mat Goebel 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:48:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello world!</title>
      <link>/p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:48:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to WordPress. This is your first post. Edit or delete it, then start writing!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Headset Instructions</title>
      <link>/post/diy-headset-instructions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/diy-headset-instructions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for the DIY clearcom headset instructions, they&amp;rsquo;re on  my old website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/a/matgoebel.com/matgoebel/projects/headset&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DIY Lightweight Clearcom Headset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/a/matgoebel.com/matgoebel/projects/diy-headset-appendix-plantronics-m130&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DIY Headset Appendix: Plantronics m130&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Article: Novel algorithm for prehospital diagnosis of STEMI</title>
      <link>/p410/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2019 16:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p410/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New article published today! &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/prehospital-and-disaster-medicine/article/novel-algorithm-for-improving-the-diagnostic-accuracy-of-prehospital-stelevation-myocardial-infarction/0C10A5E787959EFEFDA0BC9E983325BF/share/b01a901293d4f112979007cd6763ec4209d0fe66&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A Novel Algorithm for Improving the Diagnostic Accuracy of Prehospital ST-Elevation Myocardial Infarction&lt;/a&gt; in Prehospital Disaster Medicine. Follow the link for free full-text!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New article in Prehospital Emergency Care</title>
      <link>/p407/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 20:39:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p407/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve published another article, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10903127.2018.1532475&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this time in PEC.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goebel M, Tainter C, Kahn C, et al. An Urban 911 System’s Experience with Left Ventricular Assist Device Patients. Prehospital Emerg Care. October 2018:1-19. doi:10.&lt;sup&gt;1080&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;10903127&lt;/sub&gt;.2018.1532475&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UVU Magazine</title>
      <link>/p403/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 01:10:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p403/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was recently in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uvu.edu/magazine/fall2018/fall2018_paramedics.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UVU magazine article&lt;/a&gt; featuring graduates from the paramedic program who have gone on to pursue careers in medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Publication</title>
      <link>/p401/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 20:22:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p401/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0736467918303457&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prehospital Acute ST-Elevation Myocardial Infarction Identification in San Diego: A Retrospective Analysis of the Effect of a New Software Algorithm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UCSD EMIG</title>
      <link>/p398/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2018 22:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p398/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been active in UCSD SOM&amp;#8217;s Emergency Medicine Interest Group&amp;#8217;s leadership since I was an MS1.  For the 2017-18 year I&amp;#8217;ve been acting as the president &amp;#8211; coordinating all the mentoring, events, and communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/ucsdemig/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Like us on facebook!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Youtube Lectures</title>
      <link>/p378/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 21:04:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p378/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve posted lectures on youtube from conferences I&amp;#8217;ve spoken at the last several years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&#34;Killer EKGs&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pbWcjapgpOA?feature=oembed&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&#34;NSTEMIs that need the cath lab now&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2jv00CvY-0Y?start=17&amp;#038;feature=oembed&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&#34;2015 PHARM Review&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OPfIDD5eWa8?start=1588&amp;#038;feature=oembed&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&#34;Getting Better Quality EKGs&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/l38J4C2CeVQ?feature=oembed&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Textbook</title>
      <link>/p374/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 21:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p374/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The newest edition of Critical Care Transport has been published. I had the pleasure of reviewing several chapters of this textbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&#34;Critical Care Transport&#34; type=&#34;text/html&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;550&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen style=&#34;max-width:100%&#34; src=&#34;https://read.amazon.com/kp/card?preview=inline&amp;#038;linkCode=kpd&amp;#038;ref_=k4w_oembed_8icH98GeUIjkei&amp;#038;asin=B071H4LCMK&amp;#038;tag=kpembed-20&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unexpectedly in the Spotlight</title>
      <link>/p367/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 18:13:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p367/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been lucky enough to get involved with the EM:RAP crew, helping with their monthly live broadcasts. At the last show, they had a segment on DeWinter T-waves where Stuart Swadron was using an article I wrote as part of his presentation! I ended getting interviewed and answering some EKG questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-396&#34; src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/emrap.png&#34; alt=&#34;emrap&#34; width=&#34;847&#34; height=&#34;434&#34; srcset=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/emrap.png 847w, http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/emrap-300x154.png 300w, http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/emrap-768x394.png 768w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 847px) 100vw, 847px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the segment &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emrap.org/episode/emrapliveaugust/dewinterstwave&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24176590&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;publication here&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifeinthefastlane.com/winter-is-coming/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;FOAM content&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifeinthefastlane.com/ecg-library/de-winters-t-waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LITFL&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annals of Emergency Medicine Podcast</title>
      <link>/p362/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 18:08:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p362/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you aren&amp;#8217;t listening to the Annals of Emergency Medicine Audio Summary &amp;#8211; you should be. I&amp;#8217;ve been privileged to be part of the team since January. Subscribe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.annemergmed.com/content/podcast&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.annemergmed.com/content/podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My bio on the Annals website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.annemergmed.com/content/goebelbio&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.annemergmed.com/content/goebelbio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rewarding</title>
      <link>/p334/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2011 04:21:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p334/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/cpr1.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-335&#34; title=&#34;infant manikin&#34; src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/cpr1.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;217&#34; srcset=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/cpr1.jpg 535w, http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/cpr1-300x218.jpg 300w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago I became a CPR instructor for no real reason other than I wanted to. My very first CPR class had a half dozen students from the theatre department where I was doing my undergrad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward a few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get a text from one of the students in that class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Thank you for teaching me about CPR and choking. I just saved my 6 month old&amp;#8217;s life.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It stopped me dead in my tracks. Whatever it cost, however much time it took, however annoying the AHA is to deal with it, it was all worth it in that one moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I&amp;#8217;m working an extra long graveyard shift tonight, I&amp;#8217;m really looking forward to teaching CPR to a bunch of Scout leaders tomorrow who approached me because they wanted to be better prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Girl, interrupted</title>
      <link>/p158/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2010 19:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p158/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have spent literally hundred of hours with cadavers &amp;#8211; either as a students in the anatomy lab or dissecting them for those students. I&amp;#8217;m comfortable with cadavers. Really, they don&amp;#8217;t bother me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this week working in the ED I had an experience that unexpectedly shook me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a fairly busy night like any other; I was working as the EKG tech &amp;#8211; running from room to room getting 12-Leads on the usual mix of chest paineurs and overdoses. With a break in the incessant buzz of my pager, I sat down at my computer behind the nurse&amp;#8217;s station to enter orders and do assorted paperwork. I barely noticed the Vocera announcement that a trauma one was coming in. I&amp;#8217;m not a regular ED tech, and I&amp;#8217;m not signed off to work on a trauma team, so it&amp;#8217;s only something I notice in passing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My computer is next to the telemetry screens so that when I&amp;#8217;m doing paperwork I can monitor what&amp;#8217;s going on in the ED. Halfway through entering an ordering a red flash and a chime caught my eye &amp;#8212; *\&lt;em&gt;*VTAC**&lt;/em&gt;. It was in a trauma bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that moment I became aware of the huddle of nurses and techs behind me. Apparently the trauma one had become a traumatic code en route to us. Not good. We watched holding our breath as the rhythms bounced through various iterations of ACLS badness. My pager went off and I was torn away to do more 12-Leads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I passed the trauma bay a few minutes later in the course of my normal duties. CPR was in progress. I casually noted that the compressions were probably a bit faster than the AHA guidelines of 100 per minute and wondered if there was any data to suggest that there were better or worse outcomes for faster compressions. I didn&amp;#8217;t think much about the code; I was a good three pages behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later I sat down at my work station to do more paperwork. I looked at the trauma bay on telemetry: *\&lt;em&gt;*LEADS DISCONNECTED**&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s either really good or really bad. Statistically I knew what do expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that moment I overheard one of the nurses mention that they had called it just a few minutes before and were preparing the body for viewing by the family. My heart sunk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I knew that she was basically dead before she hit the ED doors, even though I wasn&amp;#8217;t on the trauma team that worked to save her, I felt culpable. It felt so wrong, knowing someone&amp;#8217;s daughter had died before her parents did. I honestly felt a little sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The familiar nagging of my pager brought me back into focus. Off to do another 12-Lead&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;#8217;t long before I needed to cross the hallway by the trauma bay again. As I approached it somehow seemed longer..emptier&amp;#8230; lonelier than I remembered. As I got closer I recognised one our social workers standing outside with her back to the bay and her head hung low. I could make out muffled whimpers and cries from the inside. My heart sank again. I took a detour through the imaging department to avoid walking past. It seemed like the right thing to do&amp;#8230;this was a very private moment for someone else. I went about my business for the remainder of the shift, avoiding the trauma bay like a crack in the sidewalk or the path of a black cat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of the shift I had some chores to do &amp;#8211; namely refilling the blanket and fluid warmers. This includes the trauma bays. I did every other part of the ED first. Then I did all the other trauma bays, hoping that I would run out of clean blankets before I got to where she was so I wouldn&amp;#8217;t have to see her&amp;#8230;no, so I wouldn&amp;#8217;t have to disturb her. I swore in my head a little when I still had blankets as my cart squeaked up to the threshold outside her room. I carefully and quietly peered in to make sure no family were present. It had been hours, but who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was on the table, laying there peacefully with her arms unnaturally still at her sides. The ETT tube was still in place. Her face and hands were ashen. The room was dark except for a single light above the table that illuminated her white draped form. Two empty chairs from the lobby flanked the table. I quietly slid in to refill the blanket and fluid warmers. The hair on the back of my neck was standing on end. My heart was racing. My mind was going even faster, calculating all the reasons that this shouldn&amp;#8217;t be happening. Every ounce of my being cried out &amp;#8220;this thing should not be.&amp;#8221; I realised that what I&amp;#8217;d felt earlier was not sickness, but sadness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I apologised for disturbing her, and not just in my head. You might think it&amp;#8217;s weird, but if you&amp;#8217;ve spent any significant amount of time working in a cadaver lab, you&amp;#8217;ve likely started talking to them. It&amp;#8217;s probably more to put me at ease, but I like to think they can hear me. Well not the physical-them that I&amp;#8217;m working with, but the spirit-them that&amp;#8217;s now out there somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished my task and took one long last look at her before my pager went off again. Someone had ordered another EKG on the panic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience genuinely spooked me. When I got home I needed my fiance to come over just so I could hold her tight and tell her I loved her. I needed to know she was okay. It took every ounce of self control not to call her and make sure she was okay the second I&amp;#8217;d head that the code was called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, why did it bother me so much in the first place? Like I said I&amp;#8217;ve spent hundreds of hours with dozens of different cadavers. What made this so different? I&amp;#8217;ve narrowed it down to a few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 &amp;#8211; She was young. Younger than me. And that&amp;#8217;s just against the natural order of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 &amp;#8211; While most don&amp;#8217;t choose death, at least cadavers in a lab have chosen to be there. A certain serenity comes from knowing that everyone is there because they want to be. That wasn&amp;#8217;t the case here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 &amp;#8211; I&amp;#8217;m used to working on a cadaver, and then learning about who they were as a person by reverse engineering their medical history and listening to family members at memorial services. To me, cadavers become people. I&amp;#8217;ve never had to mentally transition the other way from person to cadaver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope in some small way that writing this out will be therapeutic and help me organise my feelings. I know this is just the first of many of these experiences that I&amp;#8217;ll have in emergency medicine. It has to be a valuable lesson &amp;#8211; of what I&amp;#8217;m not sure yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just hope that when I close my eyes to go to sleep tonight, that I can stop seeing her face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paranoid?</title>
      <link>/p154/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2010 20:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p154/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a class=&#34;vt-p&#34; style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/spy-vs-spy-without-bombs-775529.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/spy-vs-spy-without-bombs-775529.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m paranoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My passwords for every online account are different. Many of them are randomly generated strings that are stored in an encrypted file. Common things like gmail and facebook I have memorised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understandably, I am a little leery of using a shared terminal at work to access any of my personal accounts (on my breaks of course). So what&amp;#8217;s a nerd to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, may I present to you the wonderful world of portable apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can run Google Chrome from your own personal flash drive. Chrome&amp;#8217;s incognito mode will prevent any trace of your browsing from being stores on the machine you&amp;#8217;re using. It will not mask your browsing from whatever proxies or monitoring your company is using &amp;#8211; after all if you&amp;#8217;re using their bandwidth I think they have every right to know what you&amp;#8217;re looking at, just not to store your passwords and the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So download it &lt;a href=&#34;http://portableapps.com/apps/internet/google_chrome_portable&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;{.vt-p} and put it on your flashdrive. Incognito mode is accessed by hitting control+shift+n. A new window will open with a guy who looks like he&amp;#8217;s from Spy v. Spy on the upper left corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re looking to store your passwords securely and take them with you, try &lt;a href=&#34;http://portableapps.com/apps/utilities/keepass_portable&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Keepass portable&lt;/a&gt;{.vt-p}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now for my last trick, let&amp;#8217;s talk about long distance codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re like me, you may have been seduced by Apple into buying an iPhone. Which also means, that like me, you&amp;#8217;re often unable to make or receive phone calls. Using the phone at work (on your break) may sound appealing, but you might have a problem if your employer uses long distance codes to (rightfully) control outbound phone access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a class=&#34;vt-p&#34; style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/googlevoicelogo11.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/googlevoicelogo11.jpg?w=222&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution? Google Voice. GV let&amp;#8217;s you place free long-distance calls by calling you on a land-line (so the inbound call is free) and then connecting you to the other number once you answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to make calls at work, with a long distance code and at no expense to your employer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a Google Voice account. I suggest getting the new number just so you can have free SMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Log in, click settings &amp;gt; voice settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Add another phone&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the direct dial for your work number, with a name, change the type to work, and make sure the texting box is unchecked. Click save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A box will popup. Click connect and it will call your work phone. When you answer, enter the code on the screen to confirm that you actually have access to this line. Back at the setup screen, un-check your work number so calls do not forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now when you place a GV call, you can have it connected to your work phone! No long distance code required, no cost to your employed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just be responsible. Hope you enjoyed this tip!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ETOH and Hospital Interpreters</title>
      <link>/p152/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2010 03:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p152/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In EMS and the ED many situations involve &amp;#8220;2 beers.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, in the outpatient clinic when you have a patient that doesn&amp;#8217;t speak English, they will bring a family member to interpret. That family member &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt;, however, have 2 kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will cry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will touch things they shouldn&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do such things come in pairs? The world may never know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sumdood’s Sister — “That Lady”</title>
      <link>/p142/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 04:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p142/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it sucks to fly, especially with &amp;#8220;that lady.&amp;#8221; Maybe she&amp;#8217;s realted to sumdood. Here is an open letter to, &amp;#8220;that lady:&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear &amp;#8220;that lady,&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kow you need to get places, because you seem to be on &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; flight I ever take. It&amp;#8217;s odd, because you never look the same. Must be expensive to change your appearance so radically that often. Let me offer some friendly advice to make your next flight more enjoyable &amp;#8211; mostly for me, because I know you&amp;#8217;re blisfully unaware of the effects your behaviour has on others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If have the need to transport something the size of a dead yak, kindly check it. it will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; fit in the overhead bin. PS &amp;#8211; It also freaks me out when you try to slam the plastic bin shut to make it fit. I  feel like it&amp;#8217;s going to break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;#8217;t need to be in the first boarding group, so stop throwing a fit when you aren&amp;#8217;t. &lt;em&gt;If&lt;/em&gt; your bags are appropriately sized we can all fit. And try sitting somewhere other than the front for a change &amp;#8211; that way you can hold up less than the entire plan while struggling to fit your animal carcas into the overhead bin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;#8217;ve thinned out your bag a bit so it can be crammed into overhead storage, that junk on your lap also has to go. Don&amp;#8217;t get combative when you&amp;#8217;re told it needs to be stowed. This includes any protest about needing &amp;#8220;my knitting&amp;#8221; or snacks for &amp;#8220;my blood sugar&amp;#8221; &amp;#8211; this of course spoken between fist fulls of said snack. If you lost some weight, I can almost guarantee your blood sugar would be less of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the flight attendant poked you to see if you were alive for the drink service, I was secrety hoping you weren&amp;#8217;t. I think she felt the same way, since when you didn&amp;#8217;t rouse initially and she asked me to be her &amp;#8220;witness.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thing, if you have an emergency, I am so not helping you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kthxbai&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS &amp;#8211; I&amp;#8217;ll call ahead to make sure we&amp;#8217;ve got extrication and heavy rescue when we land so there&amp;#8217;s a chance of getting your bag out of the bin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned in the ED tonight</title>
      <link>/p140/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2010 03:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p140/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight I had the opportunity to shadow my medical director while he was working in the ED. I leanred many things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every blog I&amp;#8217;ve read about how drug seekers present in the ED is completely true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every blog I&amp;#8217;ve read about faking a seizure and &amp;#8220;status dramaticus&amp;#8221; is completely true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare is a strange mash-up of completely differently evolved professions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A litre of NS and a dose of zofran will cure almost anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no mean paediatricians &amp;#8211; even when you call them at 0100 for an admission. This particular saint actually drove in an hour to evaluate the child, and still left with a smile on his face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doctors don&amp;#8217;t actually talk to or touch patients. They mostly read labs and sign things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My pre-hospital calibrated BS-detector is apparently as well refined as anyone who works in the ED full-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical patients appear to get better pain management and sedation than trauma patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare professionals do not wash their hands or use gloves nearly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More Med Math Tips: Drip Rates</title>
      <link>/p135/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2010 05:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p135/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is why 60-drip sets were invented&amp;#8230;but no one ever told me, so I feel clever having figured this out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your medication dose in mL per hour is equal to the required drips per minute when using a 60 drip set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the proof. Keep in mind that we&amp;#8217;re essentially converting units&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a class=&#34;vt-p&#34; style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{gtt}{min}%3D\frac{gtt}{min}*\frac{1ml}{60gtt}*\frac{60min}{1hour}%3D\frac{ml}{hour}&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{gtt}{min}%3D\frac{gtt}{min}*\frac{1ml}{60gtt}*\frac{60min}{1hour}%3D\frac{ml}{hour}&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that 60 drips = 1 ml, and 60 minutes = 1 hour, so we&amp;#8217;re only multiply by different versions of one to maintain equality. Drips and minutes cancel, leaving mLs and hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re using a 15-drip set, just take your mL per hour rate and divide by 4. Because&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a class=&#34;vt-p&#34; style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{1}{4}*\frac{gtt}{min}%3D\frac{1}{4}*\frac{gtt}{min}*\frac{1ml}{15gtt}*\frac{60min}{1hour}%3D\frac{ml}{hour}&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{1}{4}*\frac{gtt}{min}%3D\frac{1}{4}*\frac{gtt}{min}*\frac{1ml}{15gtt}*\frac{60min}{1hour}%3D\frac{ml}{hour}&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a 10-drip set you can try dividing by 6, but chances are that won&amp;#8217;t be easily done in your head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memorial Day – Appendix</title>
      <link>/p133/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2010 22:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p133/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some might be wondering how I wrote an entire memorial day blog without a mention of soldiers, perhaps accusing me of missing the mark or being unpatriotic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know we all occasionally forget about or take for granted those in the armed services who make the ultimate sacrifice to provide us the freedoms we hold  so dear, but it also doesn&amp;#8217;t take much to jog our memories  &amp;#8212; hopefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me point out another way our fallen soldiers continue after they die to benefit us civilians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War leads to advances in trauma care. Historically this includes everything from the invention of the IO to the resurgence of tourniquets. This year the 7th edition of Pre-hospital Trauma Life Support is coming out. A lot of the changes in those care guidelines will be fueled by the research coming out of the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some the shear amount of death in a war is beyond comprehension. But the advantage of collecting all that data is creating a scatter plot so to see what&amp;#8217;s actually killing our soldiers, then we can fix it, and then we can apply that to the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please don&amp;#8217;t think I&amp;#8217;m heartless because I&amp;#8217;m looking at the benefit of collecting data. I know that when your family is touched by tragedy all that matters to you is that single data point &amp;#8211; a human being with a family, friend, hobbies, loves, interests, and stories. I hope I made that clear in my last post about body donors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please, just recognise and remember, that after a solider makes the ultimate sacrifice (even if you object to the war) that the data collected from their death will benefit other soldiers, keeping them safe, and will eventually benefit us &amp;#8211; keeping us safe at home just like they were fighting to when they were alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memorial Day</title>
      <link>/p131/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2010 08:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p131/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I had the opportunity to attend a memorial service for the body donor programme my anatomy and dissection courses are affiliated with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;#8217;m dissecting, I see these donors in their physical entirety. I see their scars, their disease ravaged organs. I find every deformity, variation, and imperfection in their bodies. I find surgeries that suggest medical history: apendectomies, coronary bypass, hysterectomies. I find tumours. I can&amp;#8217;t help but wonder: What pain were they in? How was their disease managed? How did this happen? How long were they tormented by this? Were they glad when it was over? Sad to be gone? This person is someones son or daughter. How did their family handle everything that happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this donor very intimately in a physical (and I feel also spiritual) way, but I still know nothing about them aside from a reverse engineered medical history. I don&amp;#8217;t know who they are. I don&amp;#8217;t know what this brain thought, what these eyes saw, or what these hands did. I can&amp;#8217;t help but wonder &amp;#8211; I know the tremendous educational work this person is performing in death, but what did they do in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After both the dean of the school of medicine and the head of the emergency medicine residency programme had spoken and shared experiences about the value of having body donors, it was open mic for the donor families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family members shared stories that answered the burning questions I had. These strangers I&amp;#8217;ve been bonding with at the dissection table were civil rights activists, esteemed professors, physicians, nurses, lawyers, veterans of wars, and other just plain good people who wanted to do some good after their body is no longer of use to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the donor families don&amp;#8217;t know exactly what we&amp;#8217;re doing, but through the various speakers during the service and side conversations at the reception that followed, I hope they learned one thing: When we walk out of that room that contains their loved ones, that we are better for it. We&amp;#8217;re smarter, more skilled, more experienced clinicians. As someone who learned anatomy with a human cadaver lab, I cannot imagine the course without it. I remember one day looking at a textbook illustration, then at a photo, then at a model, and understaning how these various representations worked together to communicate an idea. Then I went to the cadaver and had to relearn it because these were abstractions of the reality on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every one of us is special and unique. I believe I first learned that lesson in grade one. However, without the generous gifts of body donors, and the incredible sarcifice of their families, medical students (paramedics, physicians, nurses, etc) would not have the ability to really see and feel how different we each are &amp;#8211; and more importantly how those differences can affect the care we will later provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I say this &amp;#8211; thank you body donors. Thank you for you generous gift. Thanks to your families for their sacrifice. They&amp;#8217;re giving you up for two years. They&amp;#8217;re putting off receiving closure for my benefit. Thank you from the bottom of my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the familes, your loved one&amp;#8217;s time is well spent. I love them and care for them knowing they are someone&amp;#8217;s son or daughter, husband or wife, father or mother, sister or brother. They give me a tour of the marvelous human body. I get the chance to see and make connections between things that other people will only ever see in artist&amp;#8217;s renditions. I get to connect the dots when I interact with a patient &amp;#8211; I know what&amp;#8217;s really going on under the hood, and it makes all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know that for as much as your loved one has affected me in the last two semesters I&amp;#8217;ve had the privilidge of working with them, that the experience they&amp;#8217;ve given me will touch the lives of every patient I encouter for my entire career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The military medevac motto is &amp;#8220;so that others may live.&amp;#8221; Your loved ones have died by some means &amp;#8211; perhaps tragic and unpreventable such as a disease that currently cannot be cured. Through this donation, their death has new meaning. While they may not cure the thing they died from, they are arming me to save lives for the rest of my career. Your family member died, and now others may live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Body donors, I salute and thank you. To the donor families, thank you also. Please sleep well at night knowing the difference you and your family are making in my life and the lives of those who I will care for in the future. Please know that I love and respect your family members. To me they are people, and I want nothing more than to know them better. Thank you for sharing them with me. Thank you for sharing the details of their lives. Thank you for helping me connect the dots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank for you making me better. Thank you from me, and from every patient I will ever touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lifeguard FAIL</title>
      <link>/p128/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2010 18:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p128/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/photo.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/photo.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weekend I&amp;#8217;m visiting southern California. My first stop after landing was a bonfire on the beach. While getting the fire going and cooking some hot dogs, I noticed a regular pattern of Lifeguard vehicles driving back and forth. Meh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while later I notice a change. One of these all-wheel-drive eco-friendly SUV&amp;#8217;s is clipping across the beach on a different path at a much faster pace. Maybe something is up&amp;#8230; but he&amp;#8217;s not running code 3, so maybe he&amp;#8217;s just in a hurry to get somewhere. A few minutes later another unit comes screaming down the beach, this time lights and sirens blaring. I know each vehicle has only one guard in it, and I&amp;#8217;m presuming that they don&amp;#8217;t have much additional medical training. I mosey over a couple hundred feet to the incident to poke my head in to see if the situation warrants offering assistance. Their patient is seated in the sand, sitting up on his own, answering questions. One guard is taking a blood pressure, the other asking questions. I have already made my &amp;#8220;from the door&amp;#8221; assessment of not sick/not hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve had multiple incidents where Lifeguards have identified themselves on a scene to insist they help, or they passed judgment on my ability to provide care (&amp;#8220;You&amp;#8217;re not from the fire department? When are the *real* EMT&amp;#8217;s getting here?&amp;#8221;). I had to resist every urge to reverse the tables for once and say &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m an EMT, I can help!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I digress. Fast forward 45 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes 45 minutes later they are still on-scene. In the distance I hear the dulcet tones of the federal Q2. An engine?&amp;#8230; And a rescue? Are they coming&amp;#8230;here? No&amp;#8230;really&amp;#8230;now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why yes&amp;#8230;45 minutes later ALS backup was called for. I also see a Coast Guard helicopter in the distance, closing in rapidly along the shore-line. Was my assessment that far off the mark? The helicopter banks over the incident and continues along the beach &amp;#8211; apparently just a coincidence. Fire Medics were on-scene for 5 minutes and then left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s understandable, being with a patient where something just doesn&amp;#8217;t feel right, you watch them and wait for them to either get worse or get better, eventually establishing whether you will release or transport. We&amp;#8217;ve all done it &amp;#8211; or at least I have. 45 minutes is a while to wait for such a decision, but I&amp;#8217;ll go along with it. Having had an ALS evaluation, I imagine our punter will be on his way any moment now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward 60 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, now the lifeguards have been on-scene for almost 2 hours.  I hear multiple sirens in the distance converging from different directions. Two stations are now responding. I meander over again just because I want to hear the exchange between the Lifeguard and the Medics. Our patient is now laying in the sand covered in a blanket. The medic walks over and simply declares &amp;#8220;I don&amp;#8217;t care, this time we&amp;#8217;re taking him! Get him on the backboard!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know hindsight is &lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;20&lt;/sub&gt; and I wasn&amp;#8217;t actually on-scene evaluating the patient &amp;#8211; but as a trained observer it seemed like this call was full of all sorts of fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lifeguards provide absolutely life savings extrication and rescue manoeuvres. They can perform BLS care early in an incident when it has the best chance of savings someone&amp;#8217;s life. But&amp;#8230;that&amp;#8217;s about all they do. Lifeguards are not God&amp;#8217;s gift to emergency response. More than once I&amp;#8217;ve been on a scene and had someone bound up to declare &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m a Lifeguard, I can help&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;ll take it from here guys.&amp;#8221; I actually had one guy try to muscle in between me and a patient. A quick glare and he was put in his place by the officer on scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my rules is that if it felt good to say it then it probably shouldn&amp;#8217;t have been said. The second time a Lifeguard did this to me on scene I said &amp;#8220;Well does it looks like he&amp;#8217;s drowning? Back off, Baywatch.&amp;#8221; He looked at me like I&amp;#8217;d kicked a puppy, then slowly sulked away. I almost felt bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tip: Kg and Pounds conversion</title>
      <link>/p118/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2010 18:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p118/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I was taking my Intermediate class, I came up with several medical math shortcuts. I&amp;#8217;m sure I&amp;#8221;m not the first person to discover these, but I figure if you stumble across my blog maybe they can be helpful to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that to get an estimation for converting pounds to kg that we can just divide by 2. Here&amp;#8217;s the problem, the actual conversion factor is much closer to 2.2 &amp;#8211; so you will always be off by 10%! That&amp;#8217;s a large margin of error in my engineer type mind. Luckily, 10% is easy to account for &amp;#8211; we just have to move the decimal over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So try this the next time you want to be more accurate going from pounds to kg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convert 170 pounds to kg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;clear:left;float:left;margin-bottom:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{170}{2}%3D85&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{170}{2}%3D85&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10% of 85 = 8.5 (move the decimal one digit left)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;85 &amp;#8211; 8.5 = 76.5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Round to 76 or 77.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s compare that to the actual conversion factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;clear:left;float:left;margin-bottom:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{170}{2.2}%20%3D%2077.27&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{170}{2.2}%20%3D%2077.27&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that taking into account that 10% makes a huge difference in the accuracy of the conversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to go from kg to pounds, multiple by 2 and then add 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nerd Speak Ahead &amp;#8212; Why this Works&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This comes down to reducing fractions. Here is the down and dirty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{pounds}{2.2}%3D\frac{pounds}{1.1*2}%3D\frac{pounds}{2}*\frac{1}{1.1}\approx\frac{pounds}{2}*0.9&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=\frac{pounds}{2.2}%3D\frac{pounds}{1.1*2}%3D\frac{pounds}{2}*\frac{1}{1.1}\approx\frac{pounds}{2}*0.9&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;31&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  Multiplying by .9 is the same and subtracting .1 from the original &amp;#8211; what we&amp;#8217;re actually doing because .1 is much easier to computer mentally. Here is the proof for that:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=(.9)*x%3D(1-0.1)*x%3Dx-(0.1)*x&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.sitmo.com/gg/latex/latex2png.2.php?z=100&amp;eq=(.9)*x%3D(1-0.1)*x%3Dx-(0.1)*x&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  I hope this helps you get more accurate drug doses quickly. I also hope you&amp;#8217;re not more confused than when you got here. Any questions? Leave a comment or drop me a line.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Education Rant</title>
      <link>/p115/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2010 01:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p115/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had a chance to help with an EMT Basic class. I was asked to teach spinal immobilisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was grinding my teeth the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we still teach to immobilise based on mechanism? Why do we seem to think that spinal immobilisation is a completely benign procedure? Why don&amp;#8217;t we teach our students to actually assess the PATIENT? Why aren&amp;#8217;t we teaching them better or new physical assessment techniques? Why don&amp;#8217;t we teach them to think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our textbooks are a few years old. They took several years to write. They were written based on accepted information and studies that were old at the time of writing. Net result: Our latest graduates have an outdated education when they finish their course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;#8217;re also tested on that outdated information by all the regulating bodies. That outdated information is our &amp;#8220;standard of care.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are we holding ourselves back? As it stands now, I think EMS is it&amp;#8217;s own worst enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BLS v ALS – my rant prompted by the EMS Garage</title>
      <link>/p114/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2010 17:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p114/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Written a while ago and saved for later publication:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;s&gt;recent &lt;/s&gt; past episode of the EMS Garage (&amp;#8220;BLS Care Is Not Dead&amp;#8221;) they talked about a question debated since the creation: BLS v ALS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, I agree. Particularly with all the points they made about education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s what uspets me. When I did my initial EMT-Basic certification I was taught &amp;#8220;what&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;when.&amp;#8221; The biggest difference in my Intermediate education was starting to think about &amp;#8220;why.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t see why I had to wait so long. Why didn&amp;#8217;t someone teach me to think this way when I was a basic? Because I did &amp;#8220;just BLS?&amp;#8221; Suddenly I have to be able to think because I can start an IV? An intervention can be just as inappropriate (BLS or ALS) if you aren&amp;#8217;t thinking about why your patient needs that therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s of much greater benefit to understand the anatomy and physiology of what&amp;#8217;s going on. When I hear &amp;#8220;difficulty breathing&amp;#8221; I don&amp;#8217;t immediately think &amp;#8220;15L/min O2 on an NRB and high-priority transport&amp;#8221; as the National Registry would have me do. I start thinking about the presentation. What could it be? Asthma? Pulmonary embolism? CHF? Pneumonia? I might not be able to do anything differently within my scope of practise, but if I know _what_ is happening to my patient, I&amp;#8217;ll know _why_ I&amp;#8217;m doing _what_ I&amp;#8217;m doing or what I&amp;#8217;m not doing. Perhaps most importantly, I can begin to predict what the heck is going to happen. I can tell them what is likely to happen when they get to the hospital. I can be honest, knowledgeable, and professional&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to diagnose. We need to understand what is happening to our patient and why. It&amp;#8217;s _not_ about procedures. It&amp;#8217;s about _thinking_ and implementing _appropriate_ interventions based on those findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And where does the chip on your shoulder come from, ALS providers? So what if your patch is different form mine? Get over yourself &amp;#8211; the things you do that _really_ make a difference, I can do too &amp;#8211; even operating as a (gasp) BASIC! Heck, the stuff that makes the biggest difference (chest compression) can (and should) be done by a bystander before either of us even gets there. Paramedics don&amp;#8217;t save cardiac arrest patients &amp;#8211; bystanders who know CPR and AED do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a unified identity as EMS providers. No matter your rank or speciality in the fire service, you identify with being a &amp;#8220;firefighter.&amp;#8221; No matter your rank or speciality in local law enforcement, you identify with being a &amp;#8220;police officer.&amp;#8221; No matter what your sub-specialty is, you all Doctors and Nurses identify with &amp;#8220;I am a Doctor/Nurse.&amp;#8221; People do not know the differences between EMT, Paramedic, and EMS. It&amp;#8217;s a great education opportunity to sit down and explain it someone, but shouldn&amp;#8217;t they understand it to begin with? Shouldn&amp;#8217;t my time be better spent talking about how to do hands-only CPR or why the flu is not an emergency? We need a unified identity. Maybe the best approach to this is to see what these words mean to the public already. Ideas define words, not the other way around. Language is ultimately arbitrary. What matters is that the ideas are agreed upon. Go ahead, call everyone a Paramedic. I know people who are &amp;#8220;just Basics&amp;#8221; that put more thought into their assessment than some Paramedics. Not all paramedics are trained/think/act/perform equally, so why be so exclusive with the title? Stop identifying yourself by what you can do, and start identifying with what you know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my major we spend a lot of time talking about language. Language changes thinking and thinking changes language. Let me give you a brief example. Before recorded music there was not live music, there was just music. Live music didn&amp;#8217;t exist because that was differentiation within. I think our EMS identity crisis is at least somewhat similar. While there are differences, the language to express them is confusing and essentially foreign to people outside of our field. If we can&amp;#8217;t to communicate with them, it&amp;#8217;s unreasonable to expect them to learn out language. We need to adapt our language to their understanding. If the language is plain enough and chosen carefully, we change how they perceive us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a lot of discussion lately about EMS education &amp;#8211; comparing us to MDs and RNs. I whole heartedly agree with those &lt;s&gt;rants&lt;/s&gt; comments. I&amp;#8217;d like to study the history of nursing to see how it is that they eventually got to be taken seriously, and figure out what we&amp;#8217;re doing wrong as an industry. Maybe our whole education system needs to be rethought. I wouldn&amp;#8217;t mind doing a paramedic residency &amp;#8211; heck that would be awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that when I eventually get my Paramedic patch and card that my education is not complete, but just starting. I know there will probably be deficits in my education, but you better believe that I&amp;#8217;m going to do everything I can to fill in those gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh&amp;#8230;and watching &amp;#8220;War Games&amp;#8221; recently&amp;#8230;I want to close by saying &lt;em&gt;never just trust the machine&lt;/em&gt;. NIBP cuff, pulseox&amp;#8230;any of it. Evil. Vital signs should be a confirmation of what you already know from a good physical assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Said at Inservice Tonight</title>
      <link>/p112/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2010 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p112/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We were discussing possible causes for sycope in paediatric patients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: Could be cardiac. Maybe a congenital heart defect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lecturer: Yes, very good. Let&amp;#8217;s define that word for anyone who doesn&amp;#8217;t know it. For starters, it has nothing to do with the genitals. (collective giggle) This is your heart. Here I&amp;#8217;ll make the left ventricle bigger so it&amp;#8217;s anatomically correct. And here are the pacemakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/thumpy.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/thumpy.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Face palm. I used to wonder why people make fun of us for being &amp;#8220;just BLS.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess that answers that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CPR Recert Revenge</title>
      <link>/p110/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2010 23:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p110/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/cpr.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/cpr.gif?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;246&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  In my feeble attempts to make myself more valuable, I went ahead and got an AHA Instructor certification. Yes, I am a CPR instructor but have never had a chance to do CPR on a real patient. Still, I know all the protocols and procedures, ratio, etc., forward, backward, inside and out. My EMS Coordinator asked me to help with skills testing for CPR recertification this year.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several of the EMTs in my agency are also anatomy TAs at my university. Even though &lt;a href=&#34;http://nerdymedic.blogspot.com/2009/12/bragging-rights.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;I did rather well&lt;/a&gt; in anatomy, I have some&amp;#8230;ill feelings toward about the difficulty of some of the pins on my exams. Since they&amp;#8217;re all senior TAs, they are the ones pinning the exams. A &amp;#8220;normal&amp;#8221; TA that just teaches a section and pins weekly quizzes I could easily forgive, but these guys&amp;#8230; I had no choice but to give them a hard time since I was now in the position of test-giver rather than test-taker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I go through this&amp;#8230;they all passed with flying colours, following AHA guidelines to the letter. It was just so easy to mess with them&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TA: Okay, I&amp;#8217;m going to open the airway with a head-tilt chin lift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA, clicking pen: Oh, really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TA: I&amp;#8230;uh&amp;#8230;yeah&amp;#8230;yeah I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: Well&amp;#8230;okay&amp;#8230;if that&amp;#8217;s what you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TA: Okay I&amp;#8217;m checking for a pulse for 5-10 seconds. Is there a pulse?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: Well, I don&amp;#8217;t know &amp;#8211; is there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TA: I guess not&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: Well, it&amp;#8217;s a manakin of course there isn&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TA: Oh, ok&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: (evil cackle)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I feel bad? No, not really. They all performed their skills flawlessly, so the integrity of the test was not compromised at all &amp;#8211; and I feel much better now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;#8217;m only doing skills testing and not involved in the actual teaching, I like to ask a couple supplemental questions to make sure they really know their stuff. One of the questions I usually ask is what tidal volume is appropriate for ventilation / how much of the bag do you squeeze? Realising that I was dealing with people just as geek as me, I had the following conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: Alright, K how much of the bag are you going to be using when you ventilate the patient?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;K: About half to prevent hyperventilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: OMG OMG OMG! I can talk to you about inter-thoracic pressure and cardiac perfusion pressure and you&amp;#8217;ll understand!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;K: Talk nerdy to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then went on to explain how hyperventilating the patient can be very detrimental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;K: OMG that makes so much sense!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: I KNOW! Isn&amp;#8217;t anatomy amazing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;K: Yes! Anatomy TA Handshake!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA&amp;amp;K doing the secret handshake: Cross-bars of flesh!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only know the secret handshake because I spent so much time in the lab while I was taking the class. They sort of adopted me. Nerds FTW!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons in communication and narcs</title>
      <link>/p108/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2010 22:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p108/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m responding to a sports injury, paged as a broken arm. Upon arrival we quickly triangulate the patient&amp;#8217;s location from the screams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume patient care. The probie who would normally be interfacing with the patient has a sort of glassy look that says. &amp;#8220;OMFG a real injured person!&amp;#8221; Had I allowed him to begin his assessment, it would have quickly deteriorated into &amp;#8220;um&amp;#8230;do you have any allergies?&amp;#8221; without having even touched the patient. I&amp;#8217;ve noticed that new EMT&amp;#8217;s have a strong tendency to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expose the extremity. She has an extra elbow. I need to remove a guard to see if the fracture is open or closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m going to cut this off.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patient, looking over: &amp;#8220;WHAT?! Is it that bad?!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: &amp;#8220;Oh, um. I meant this guard type-y thingy.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add that one to the &amp;#8220;oops list.&amp;#8221; Lesson learned about using precise language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m again caught off guard by the strong correlation between dispatch information and the actual call. Twice now? Weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fire Department arrives to transport the patient to hospital. I&amp;#8217;ve completed my assessment, but held off splinting so they could first provide some pain relief. 10mg of morphine later, her screams and grimace have been converted to moans and a sort of glassy-faced grin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patient: &amp;#8220;My arm feels fine now. Do I still have to go to the hospital?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medic, clapping O2 mask on her: &amp;#8220;Um, yeah.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;s&gt;bite my tongue to stifle my laughter&lt;/s&gt; professionally maintain my composure with the Fire Crew (who seems to be having the same challenge) and help lift the patient onto the stretcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>University took my circadian rhythm and shot it between the eyes</title>
      <link>/p105/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2010 22:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p105/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230; but napping is keeping it on life support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a university student, EMT, and someone who has worked in technical theatre professionally for almost 10 years, I am intimately familiar with exhaustion and sleep deprivation. I share with those who may stumble across this, my intimate knowledge of napping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Napping is awesome for increasing your alertness, productivity, and cognitive function. It combats sleepiness, which can be hazardous when providing patient care or operating a vehicle. If you&amp;#8217;re a student, it can also be hazardous to your grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;1 &amp;#8211; Introduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important aspect of a nap is the duration. Secondarily, there are a some adjuncts you can use to increase the quality of your sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/sleep_cycle.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/sleep_cycle.jpeg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sleep-problems.com/sleep_architecture/stages_of_sleep/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;Apple-style-span&#34; style=&#34;font-size:small;&#34;&gt;Photo credit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure above is your sleep cycle. You can see that you go from being awake, to deep sleep, back to nearly waking, over and over until you awake (ideally) from a &amp;#8220;shallow&amp;#8221; REM sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever wake up and just can&amp;#8217;t seem to get moving? That&amp;#8217;s called &lt;strong&gt;sleep inertia&lt;/strong&gt;, and it&amp;#8217;s normally caused by a disagreement with your sleep cycle. You most likely woke up in deep instead of shallower sleep, so your body wasn&amp;#8217;t ready to wake up. If you had slept a little less or a little more, you would have been fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s not very clear from the graphic above, but an average person&amp;#8217;s sleep cycle is around 90 minutes. Meaning, you go from waking, to deep sleep, nearly back to waking in an hour and a half. After you go to sleep, you really start to plummet into deep sleep after 20-30 minutes, and you won&amp;#8217;t be near waking again until the end of the 90 minute cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;2 &amp;#8211; Duration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding your sleep cycle is the key to getting an energising nap. Since we want to wake up from a shallow sleep in order to avoid sleep inertia, our naps need to &lt;strong&gt;less than 30 minutes or at least 90&lt;/strong&gt;.  You may need to tweak these times based on how your personal sleep cycle exactly works. If you&amp;#8217;ve spent any time studying anatomy or physiology, you know that everybody is a little different. I can&amp;#8217;t stress enough that this is the biggest part of getting naps right &amp;#8211; the duration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;3 &amp;#8211; Adjuncts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we can use adjuncts to increase the quality of our nap and help us get to sleep faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A. Sleep Mask&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/sleep-mask1.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/sleep-mask1.jpeg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://leisureguy.wordpress.com/2006/08/02/tips-for-better-sleep/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;Apple-style-span&#34; style=&#34;font-size:small;&#34;&gt;Photo Credit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:normal;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  You will never realise how much ambient light kept you from getting to sleep until you try using a sleep mask. Since you, as a medical professional, will likely be seeking napping bliss at all hours, these can he a huge help. Sleep masks have some different qualities or features you should be aware of when purchasing. Expect to spend around $20 for a decent one.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Material&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8211; Masks come in nylon and cotton. Many people prefer the cotton or cloth-like materials. Consider going to a store and feeling a couple to decide what you prefer.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Light Blocking&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8211; You would think that all sleep masks are 100% like blocking, but they aren&amp;#8217;t. Cheap nylon ones allow some light through and will annoy you. Most quality sleep masks that you will find for purchase will block all light. It&amp;#8217;s normally the cheap complimentary ones you get that will leak.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Padding&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8211; Nicer sleep masks will feature padding in the periorbital region to keep the mask from laying completely against your eyes, as this can be annoying.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Ear plug storage&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8211; if you choose to use earplugs, it can be convenient to store them in your sleep mask.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;B. Ear Plugs&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/mmm3404004_1_12.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/mmm3404004_1_12.jpeg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://a.%20sleep%20mask/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;Apple-style-span&#34; style=&#34;font-size:small;&#34;&gt;Photo Credit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  This might sound familiar, but you won&amp;#8217;t realise how much ambient noise was distracting you from sleep until you use earplugs. There are a couple things to consider when purchasing earplugs. You should only need to spend, at most, a couple dollars on a pair of earplugs.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Noise Reduction Rating&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8211; All earplugs are given a noise reduction rating in dBNR (decibels of noise reduction) that is the number of decibels the earplugs reduce ambient sound when worn &lt;em&gt;correctly&lt;/em&gt;. The decibel scale is logarithmic and was modelled after the sensitivity of human hearing. Every 10 dB is factor of two (twice/half as loud), so earplugs with a 20dBNR rating would only allow 1/4 of the ambient sound into your ears.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Material/Construction&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8211; Most of the earplugs you&amp;#8217;ve ever seen are probably the foam kind you&amp;#8217;re meant to squish and roll up to place in the external auditory meatus. These can be very comfortable, but are easily worn incorrectly. When it comes to disposable earplugs, I prefer the triple flanged rubber type pictured above.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  If you&amp;#8217;re &lt;em&gt;serious&lt;/em&gt; about earplugs for occupational reasons (or whatever), you can see an audiologist and order custom fitted earplugs. I&amp;#8217;ve had great success with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.earinc.com/index.php&#34;&gt;EAR Inc&lt;/a&gt;. If you go the custom route, you can easily spend $100 or more for fitted &amp;#8220;musician&amp;#8221; earplugs. However, you&amp;#8217;ll only want simple solid silicone molds for napping. These will cost considerably less, probably only $40 total, but I&amp;#8217;m not completely sure as I&amp;#8217;ve only ever ordered the musician type.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;C. Caffeine&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://nerdymedic.files.wordpress.com/2010/01/070815_coke_vmed_11awidec2.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://nerdymedic.files.wordpress.com/2010/01/070815_coke_vmed_11awidec2.jpeg?w=162&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://coolaggregator.wordpress.com/2008/06/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;Apple-style-span&#34; style=&#34;font-size:small;&#34;&gt;Photo Credit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  You might be thinking, &amp;#8220;how on earth can caffeine helper rather than hinder a nap?&amp;#8221; We all know that after it&amp;#8217;s ingested, caffeine will take some time to actually be absorbed and have any effect. Luckily this happens to be around the same length of time our short nap will be. So, if you quickly drink some caffeine, then take a 20-30 minute nap, when coming out of it you will have the combined benefits of the sleep and the caffeine. Caffeinated power naps are &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;4 &amp;#8211; Conclusion / Summary&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/google_cat_nap2.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/google_cat_nap2.jpeg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.catsarepeople2.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;Apple-style-span&#34; style=&#34;font-size:small;&#34;&gt;Photo Credit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  Naps are amazing. Use them. Sleep less than 30 minutes. If you need to sleep more, then go for at least 90. Use a sleep mask and earplugs to improve how quickly you fall asleep. Pound some caffeine right before a 20-30 minute nap for an extra pick me up.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  Lather, Rinse, Repeat.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It’s very difficult to do compressions on a pug</title>
      <link>/p95/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 03:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p95/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last night I went to an annual Christmas after-party at a close friend&amp;#8217;s house. He&amp;#8217;s graduating from vet school this year, so naturally our conversation turned to medicine. I was particularly interested in comparing the emergency care of animals and humans. Several things had plagued me on the windy drive up to his house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, they really did plague me. My nickname is &amp;#8220;Nerd Alert&amp;#8221; for a good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Hey D, you ever code a dog?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;What do you mean?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Like&amp;#8230;lethal cardiac arrhythmia, CPR, shock, intubate, epi, atropine, ya know?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Oh yeah. I wasn&amp;#8217;t sure what you were asking because when an animal checks in we ask what code they are:  DNR, CPR only, or Heroic CPR.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Heroic CPR? You have my attention&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Uh, that&amp;#8217;s not what they actually call it. But basically we&amp;#8217;re going to pull out all the stops &amp;#8211; internal chest compression, everything you would do on a human, the whole 9 yards. Usually the animal is basically dead, so everything else is done for heroics.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Have you ever done CPR on a dog?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Yeah once on a pug in surgery. He was kind of round though, so he kept rolling as I was pushing and we&amp;#8217;d have to stop and put him back in position.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I whipped out my iPhone and show him &lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.me/p1ELb1-1r&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my new favourite app&lt;/a&gt;. He is astonished that humans have &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the same muscles. I ask him about anatomical differences between different animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Meh, a mammal is pretty much a mammal. There&amp;#8217;s really only some minor differences.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our conversation turns to interventions. IVs, IOs, intubation, ECGs &amp;#8211; vets do it all too! Although, apparently IOs are pretty much reserved for birds. When a dog is intubated they&amp;#8217;re placed prone with their chin on the table &amp;#8211; which puts them in what we would call the sniffing position. From there it&amp;#8217;s pretty much a straight shot down the trachea. &lt;em&gt;Sometimes&lt;/em&gt; a laryngoscope with a large blade is used to manipulate the tongue, but about half the time it&amp;#8217;s not necessary at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forgot to ask about bag-valve-mask technique. Oh well, that will be good conversation at his graduation party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also talked about medication dosages. The meds are calculated the same as human ped doses. I told him about broslow tape and ped boxes. We may or may not have a million dollar idea in adapting broslow tape to veterinary medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily no one reads this blog, so our idea is safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We’ve got a bleeder!</title>
      <link>/p93/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 03:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p93/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tones drop for a male with a bleeding disorder that cut his finger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Band-aid brigade to the rescue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrive to find our patient loosely holding a paper towel over the injury. That&amp;#8217;s less than helpful, but I&amp;#8217;ll give you a B for effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grab his finger with a 4&amp;#215;4 (hey, it was handy), elevate, and squeeze hard enough to turn the distal segment white.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get to talking &amp;#8211; OPQRST and all that. Turn&amp;#8217;s out he&amp;#8217;s been bleeding for a few hours now. Excuse me? Let&amp;#8217;s talk about this bleeding disorder&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently the last time he had received so much as a minor scratch, it took nearly a &lt;strong&gt;week&lt;/strong&gt; to stop bleeding. Oh, and he&amp;#8217;s never seen a doctor about it. Of course not, why would he do that? At this point I check the 4&amp;#215;4. Still bleeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fine. This is a good excuse to let the probie crack an ice pack. Slap that on, see what happens. A few minutes later he&amp;#8217;s still bleeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fine. I find a brachial pulse, ask the probie to push here. A few minutes late the bleeding has&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230; slowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmmm&amp;#8230; Well&amp;#8230; I&amp;#8230; Uh&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it is the next step in bleeding control, on principle I refuse to put a tourniquet on something that amounts to a papercut. Just no. The patient reports that he is now feeling dizzy. I get a fresh set of vitals to fins his heart rate is elevated for someone who has been sitting on the couch. Really? Hypovolaemia from a paper cut? Really? It&amp;#8217;s _just_ a papercut? Is this seriously happening?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fine. Let&amp;#8217;s go to the hospital We hop into &lt;s&gt;the gutless wonder&lt;/s&gt; our vehicle and tear off to St Closets as fast as we can &amp;#8211; meaning a snail could easily outpace us. On our way to the hospital I call ahead and ask if they would like me to drop our patient off in the waiting room or go through the ambulance door. I&amp;#8217;m told it&amp;#8217;s slow, so to come on through the ambulance doors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sliding doors open and the charge nurse glances at the three of us walking into the ED, realising that our patient is indeed holding a 4&amp;#215;4 over their thumb. She gives me a stern look over her glasses. Without saying a word, she speaks volumes. _Are you seriously bringing &amp;#8220;I hurted my finger&amp;#8221; to my level 2 trauma centre?_ Her criticism resonates in my skulls like she&amp;#8217;s communicated telepathically. Unfortunately, tin foil hats are not part of our standard PPE, so I have no protection from her silent criticism as I walk my patient to the indicated room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;St Closets is the only hospital in my city, so it could also be called St Onlys. This was also before the hospital opened an urgent care clinic, so the ED is the only medical attention you can get outside of business hours. Yes Nurse Ratched, I am bringing you my patient with her boo-boo. And I&amp;#8217;m doing it proudly, as we at the band-aid brigade rarely get to transport patients. So if you please, kiss it and make it better, and we&amp;#8217;ll be out of your hair before the Fire Department can bring you the town drunk for the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I give my handoff to an equally sceptical nurse at the bedside. She sees that our patient has now bled through the 4&amp;#215;4 I applied earlier. A tech puts on a fresh one and matter-of-factly adds a pressure dressing. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;There&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; he seems to say as he walks out of the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I poke my head in 20 minutes later. The pressure dressing has bled through. &lt;em&gt;Told ya so.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A physician , nurse, and tech enter the room with a shared look of consternation/frustration/irritation/annoyance/awe/disbelief. It&amp;#8217;s decided to stitch it shut. Yes, what amounts to a paper cut is about to be stitched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two stitches later the bleeding is finally controlled. The &amp;#8220;injury&amp;#8221; is then covered in fresh pressure dressing and splinted to prevent any movement from tearing the stitches. With all this wound care, our patient&amp;#8217;s thumb is now at least five times its normal size. His face seems to say, &amp;#8220;FML.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;s&gt;chuckle&lt;/s&gt; keep a straight face and very professionally call us back in service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coolest. iPhone. app. ever.</title>
      <link>/p89/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2009 08:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p89/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever wish you could visit the cadaver lab in your spare minutes between classes? Or even during a boring class (&lt;strong&gt;cough&lt;/strong&gt; dramatic literature &lt;strong&gt;cough&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  There&amp;#8217;s an app for that.Short-partner told me about an iPhone app a long while ago that sounded pretty cool&amp;#8230; but because I was frequently dropped on my head as a child, I never got around to looking it up. Then it was &lt;a href=&#34;http://streetanatomy.com/2009/12/08/pocket-cadaver/&#34;&gt;featured&lt;/a&gt; on my new favourite blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.streetanatomy.com/&#34;&gt;Street Anatomy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; 
  
  &lt;div&gt;
    Introducing &amp;#8220;Pocket Cadaver.&amp;#8221; OMG I wish I&amp;#8217;d gotten around to finding this while I was still taking anatomy. You can do through all these layers of the beautifully done cadaver dissection, highlight and label structures, rotate, zoom in and out, and even &lt;em&gt;search&lt;/em&gt; for a structure and have it show you where it is. Amazing! I just wish the imagery were higher resolution. Maybe in an update.
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;http://anatomylab.com/iphone/anatomylab.html&#34;&gt;Online demo&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;http://thinkanatomy.com/2009/12/anatomylab-app/&#34;&gt;Review and purchasing link&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/5banatomy2blab52.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/5banatomy2blab52.jpeg?w=200&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Most beautiful blog ever</title>
      <link>/p87/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2009 08:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p87/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason I did so well in anatomy was because I developed a deep love for the human body and the beauty of it&amp;#8217;s construction. It goes along with the whole &amp;#8220;nerd&amp;#8221; persona. I stumbled across a new blog the other day, and it is a sort of anatomy &amp;#8220;nerdvana.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.streetanatomy.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Street Anatomy&lt;/a&gt; features all sorts of beautiful uses of anatomy in medicine, art, and design. I particularly enjoy their &amp;#8220;Anatomic Fashion Friday&amp;#8221; feature. I like it so much, I made some last minute additions to my christmas list. The site also features beautiful art work. Some of it I&amp;#8217;m actually going to buy prints of. Some of it will just grace my desktop as wallpaper. So please, click, enjoy, geek out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_Sidebar: _I&amp;#8217;m not the only one who enjoy this stuff. After I shared it with my friend &lt;a href=&#34;http://medicdani.blogspot.com/2009/12/if-you-have-time-to-burn.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dani, she posted it on her blog&lt;/a&gt;. And she&amp;#8217;s cool. So neener-neener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.behance.net/Gallery/anatomy-sketchbook/239697&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; series &lt;a href=&#34;http://streetanatomy.com/2009/07/16/anatomy-sketchbook-done-right/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;featured on the blog&lt;/a&gt; particularly gorgeous. It fuses two of my favourite things: anatomy and technical drawing/sketching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear:both;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a style=&#34;margin-left:1em;margin-right:1em;&#34; href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/10547512442326322.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/10547512442326322.jpeg?w=232&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maybe that acting class was useful after all</title>
      <link>/p86/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2009 04:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p86/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tones drop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  EMS respond on a mid 20&amp;#8217;s male having an asthma attack. Patient does not have their inhaler.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  First though: This could be &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_0&#34;&gt;lejit&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Second though: But probably not.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Off to the scene we scream in the gutless wonder. When we arrive on scene I talk to the officer who is already there.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;Um&amp;#8230;so when I reported asthma&amp;#8230; I meant &lt;em&gt;asthma&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  I glance at the patient. There is no apparent distress. He appears to be &amp;#8220;status &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_1&#34;&gt;dramaticus&lt;/span&gt;.&amp;#8221; In other words, there is no medical problem, but instead this is mostly likely anxiety related. That&amp;#8217;s fine &amp;#8211; we all have &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_2&#34;&gt;stressors&lt;/span&gt;. Sometimes people just need to be talked down. That&amp;#8217;s a legitimate intervention.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;Got it&amp;#8230;asthma with a lowercase &amp;#8216;a&amp;#8217; &amp;#8220;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;You got it&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Because this is a simple call with no real life threats, I will let the &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_3&#34;&gt;probie&lt;/span&gt; I&amp;#8217;m with take patient care. His interaction with the patient goes something like this.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;Hi, I&amp;#8217;m &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_4&#34;&gt;probie&lt;/span&gt; with the band-aid brigade, what&amp;#8217;s going on today?&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Cold Stare
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;Hey are you doing okay?&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Cold Stare
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;&lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_5&#34;&gt;Heellloooooo&lt;/span&gt;?&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;GO AWAY! I&amp;#8217;M FINE! I HATE YOU!&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    I reach for the &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_6&#34;&gt;pulseox&lt;/span&gt;. This was dispatched and coded for difficulty breathing, so I should document that he was, in fact, &amp;#8220;fine.&amp;#8221; I&amp;#8217;m within an inch of the &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_7&#34;&gt;patient&amp;#8217;s&lt;/span&gt; finger when he erupts with a guttural scream not heard outside the deepest pits of hell until this very moment.
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div&gt;
    &amp;#8220;GET THAT THING AWAY FROM ME!&amp;#8221;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div&gt;
    I whip off my glove, put the pulseox on myself, and hold it directly in front of his face. &amp;#8220;It goes like this. It won&amp;#8217;t hurt you. Just take a deep breath.&amp;#8221;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div&gt;
    With a pout the patient thrusts me an index finger. I get a quick reading and pull it off just as he starts screaming again.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_8&#34;&gt;Probie&lt;/span&gt; gives me the deer-in-the-headlights look. I step in. Here is the abridged version of the dialogue:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;Hey, I&amp;#8217;m &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_9&#34;&gt;NerdAlert&lt;/span&gt;. I know you&amp;#8217;re not happy we&amp;#8217;re here, but &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_10&#34;&gt;someone&amp;#8217;s&lt;/span&gt; called 911 so we need to make sure you&amp;#8217;re okay.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;M FINE LEAVE ME ALONE!&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;Right. We need to make &lt;em&gt;sure&lt;/em&gt; you&amp;#8217;re fine.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;GO AWAY I HATE YOU!&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  By now I have been on-scene for several minutes and have not gotten very far. I sit for a moment, pondering where to go next, absorbing some more verbal abuse, when I remember something from an acting class I was forced to take for my major. In a situation like this, where a scene has grown stagnant, it is often appropriate to change &amp;#8220;tactics&amp;#8221; &amp;#8211; or in other words try to get what you want in a different way.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;Well you know what?&lt;strong&gt; You &lt;/strong&gt;dont&amp;#8217;t want me here and &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; don&amp;#8217;t want to be here. So the sooner you let me do &lt;strong&gt;my&lt;/strong&gt; job the sooner &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; can leave. &lt;strong&gt;Alright&lt;/strong&gt;?&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;FINE!&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;GOOD! Now let my partner take your blood pressure.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;M FINE!&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &amp;#8220;Fine people let us take their blood pressure. &lt;strong&gt;Now roll up your sleeve!&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;#8220;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Patient complies with appropriate dramatic flair.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The officer, standing behind the patient this entire time, gives me a big thumbs up.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Sometimes you just have to switch tactics.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bragging Rights</title>
      <link>/p84/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2009 03:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p84/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/204725_7kcqu1kqbn3qqu4v2bkfsl8q_.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/204725_7kcqu1kqbn3qqu4v2bkfsl8q_.jpeg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;Apple-style-span&#34; style=&#34;color:#0000ee;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration:underline;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t like people who brag, and I don&amp;#8217;t like being one of them. Sometimes, though, events call for celebration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I decided to really start pursuing emergency medicine as a career over technical theatre. As such, I took Human Anatomy this semester. I sat in on the lectures for a semester before I took it to see what I was getting into. I was afraid. Very afraid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest part of the course that people talk about is the lab. Hundreds and hundreds of new terms. Find them on this cadaver, in that specimen, on this model, in this illustration. What it&amp;#8217;s structural classification? Functional? What kind of epithelial tissue is it? What hormones does it secrete? What&amp;#8217;s it&amp;#8217;s origin? Insertion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head asplode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought the lab manual and spent all summer learning just the bones. That was two weeks of material? It took me three months to get comfortable with this. I could lose my scholarship. FML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came the first day in lab. I kept up with my TA for about the first 30 minutes of the 2 hour lab. After that my head was full. Why are you still talking to me? Words come out of your mouth, TA, but it sounds like you&amp;#8217;re speaking in tongues. Did I just have a stroke?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went to open lab &amp;#8211; free study time with TAs to get all the information you missed in your proper lab section &amp;#8211; meaning probably most of it. 6 hours a week. By the time my weekly quiz rolled around I found myself standing next to the TA teaching other students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the quizzes went well. &amp;#8220;That&amp;#8217;s to be expected,&amp;#8221; I thought. We were still reviewing the material I had self-taught over the summer. D-day would be week 3: upper body muscles. But that came and went. The nice thing about sciences is that you can always put more time in. It&amp;#8217;s got nothing to do with your feelings (&lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt; theatre &lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt;); it&amp;#8217;s either right or wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the midterm I could count on one hand the number of pins I had missed. It was a good feeling, and a lot of people disliked me for it. But they didn&amp;#8217;t spend 6 hours a week studying in open lab. They complained about how cold the specimens were. They complained about the smells. They complained about the relentless onslaught of new terms. What they didn&amp;#8217;t do was study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there were the lectures. 2 hours per week with it&amp;#8217;s own separate language, and it has everything to do with the lab because&amp;#8230; They&amp;#8217;re both about humans? That&amp;#8217;s about where the overlap ended. 3 more hours per week of review sessions. At least the TA was cute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between lecture and lab I spent an average of 12 hours per week either in class or in reviews/open lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lecture midterm 1: 94%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lecture midterm 2: 95%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lecture Final: 91%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lab midterm: 98%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lab Final: 99%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall grade 96%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solid A in a class I was scared to death of. Take that stuck up pre-med and nursing students. pwn3d. And I didn&amp;#8217;t use a single word that ends in -ism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe this medicine thing will work out after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This is not a pipe</title>
      <link>/p82/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2009 07:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p82/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/magritte-not-a-pipe.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/magritte-not-a-pipe.jpeg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#551a8b;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rule #1: Any correlation between the dispatch and the actual call is strictly a coincidental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Dispatcher: Band-aid brigade, copy medical. Swimming accident at the local pool. At least one patient. Lifeguards have backboarded the first patient.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Groan. Clear across our response area for a stubbed toe? There are a number of assumed facts here that could easily be wrong. We go en route. Our supervisor beats us to the scene by just a minute or so.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Supervisor: Dispatch, we have a single patient. Lifeguards are holding c-spine. Patient is complaining of neck pain and tingling in her feet. Let&amp;#8217;s roll city fire on this.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  I cough a little bit on my water bottle as I sit shotgun. Seriously? Normally I do all I can do rule out immobilisation. I think backboarding based on mechanism, as most people are taught in Basic class, is stupid. Mechanism informs your index of suspicion, not your treatment. And truth be told, certain combinations of physical assessment indicators are &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; accurate than a reading of an x-ray or a CT. But&amp;#8230; based on this update the guy already qualifies under every spinal criteria I know.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  We roll up and the supervisor already on scene gives me a hand off. I tell the lifeguard she&amp;#8217;s doing a great job holding c-spine and it&amp;#8217;ll help us if she can keep it up. I&amp;#8217;m going to need my hands.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  I lean directly over the patient so she doesn&amp;#8217;t have to move her head. &amp;#8220;Hi, I&amp;#8217;m nerd alert with the band-aid brigade. What&amp;#8217;s going on?&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Alert and Oriented x4, Glasgow of 15, tracking well. These are all good thing. Now how about that neck pain. Tell me if this hurts. It does? That&amp;#8217;s close to mid-line. Crap.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Squeeze my hands, wiggle your toes, you said your feet tingle? Crap. Collar on.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Crap. This is my first even potentially legitimate spinal. Crap. Crap. Crap.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Luckily the patient is &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; in textbook &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resusci_Anne&#34;&gt;Resusci-Anni&lt;/a&gt; position, and I am with 5 other people that are trained how to backboard.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Right. Now, stand back, deep breath, and think this through completely. Have everyone else do the doing.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  C-spine taken. ABCs are okay.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  D(isability) has been established. I said she was in &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; textbook position. A quick 5 person lift and a slide of the board and things are managed.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  E(xposure). She&amp;#8217;s starting to shiver and has a decreasing LOC. I noticed the tile was cold while I was kneeling. The backboard has her off the ground. Extra Lifeguard get some towels and dry her off as best she can. Probie go out to the vanbulance and fetch fresh blankets.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  F(arenheit). Vitals, please include a tympanic temp. 98º. Well that&amp;#8217;s less bad.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  G(et Vitals). Hypertensive. Not good considering this all started with a head truma, but nothing to be done about that at the BLS level other than document it.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  H(ead-to-toe assessment). She&amp;#8217;s still shivering. I had a quick peek before she was covered up, and she was completely alert when denying other injuries. Sooooo&amp;#8230;..I&amp;#8217;ll save this for the hospital when she&amp;#8217;s dry and warm and can participate completely in the assessment. Yeah, that&amp;#8217;s it.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  I(nspect the back). Had a quick palpation when we slid her on the board. Nothing remarkable, but no visual inspection happening now that she&amp;#8217;s immobilised.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  City fire arrives. I give my hand off. One SAMPLE history later and she&amp;#8217;s being loaded up to go to hospital. I&amp;#8217;m getting ready to ask the medic if I can ride along (an Intermediates running with a BLS agency craves that chance for an IV stick like a fish does water) when Supervisor throws a probie in the back of the Rescue for the ride in.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Dammit. Thus endeth the call.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The moral of the story is that rule 1 always applies, and when you size up the call in your head prepare for the least expected &amp;#8211; that the dispatch might actually be right!
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sick or old?</title>
      <link>/p81/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2009 02:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p81/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I like EMS is because it can be intellectually challenging. I had a call recently that I thought was going to turn into an episode of House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was paged to an elderly female who had fainted. BFD. Geriatric DFO. I let the probie take patient care while I sat back with my &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m-trying-to-look-cool-and-get-a-date-from-being-in-uniform&amp;#8221; shades on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probie: Hey m&amp;#8217;am we&amp;#8217;re the band-aid brigaid. What seems to be going on today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patient: *blank stare*&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;*blink*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probie: Uh&amp;#8230;. *gives me the puppy look*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: *grunt, stooping down directly in front of patient to make eye contact* Hello, M&amp;#8217;am? Are you alright? What&amp;#8217;s going on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patient finally started responding. She wasn&amp;#8217;t tracking well, but did better when I spoke louder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sick or old?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were taking a hot shower when you started feeling &amp;#8220;not well&amp;#8221; then bent over to pick something up and almost passed out. Caught herself and deny any injury. Deny (and bystanders confirm) any of loss of consciousness. Well, fine. You look okay to me right now. But you&amp;#8217;re old and you deserve to be thrown on a monitor just on that alone. Sadly we&amp;#8217;re just a BS, er, BLS agency &amp;#8211; we&amp;#8217;re not very good but we try hard. Probably not a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sick or old?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radial pulse is strong and regular at a good rate. Blood pressure is normal. Respirations appear fine. Cold and clammy but she&amp;#8217;s half dressed and still wet. Fine, have probie get a towel to dry her off, get her dressed, and get the blanket from the vanbulance. Yes I&amp;#8217;m fine with your son giving you a ride home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That cough sounds nasty. It started after you almost fell? Okay&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lung sounds are clear. Sats are good. No chest pain or difficulty breathing. Just a cough. Not a PE?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sick or old?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PD have contacted the son to give her a ride home. Fine, treat and release. She seems to be doing okay. But Intermediate class taught to think about the &amp;#8220;why&amp;#8221; not just the &amp;#8220;what.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did you almost fall? I don&amp;#8217;t like what I&amp;#8217;m seeing. My gut says you need a better work up. Something. is. wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peripheral vasodilation from the warm water after your work out? Negative orthostatics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;#8217;t look hypoglycaemic. And my meter tells me the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auscultate heart sounds. Normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stroke exam? Extremely minor facial droop, minor arm drift. No speech slurring. Pupils are equally round, but you have a minor relative afferent pupilary defect. TIA? or just old? At least I have a leg to stand on when I tell you to go the ED after your son gets here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More coughing. Some extra saliva. &amp;#8220;I feel like I might vomit.&amp;#8221; GI Symptoms? No belly pain. Check blood pressure across both arms, auscultate between the scapulae. No, probably not a AAA. MI? Certainly not a normal presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My spidey sense is tingling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sick or old?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh what&amp;#8217;s that? Saw your doctor today and he wants you to come back for blood work tomorrow? Well that would have been great to know the first time I asked. Yes and the meds you couldn&amp;#8217;t remember earlier are warfarin and a beta blocker. Fantastic. Definitely and ED trip for you. But no need for ambulance, no, your son will be here soon and the cardiac centre is only a few blocks away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m getting the stair chair when dispatch tells me the son is at least 20 minutes out. I get back inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probie: She got really dizzy again and her pulse dropped to 40, but it&amp;#8217;s back up now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: *under breath* balls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I smell something cardiac and I want a monitor. I call for City Fire. By the time they arrive her palpable pulse is irregular. 3-lead shows a-fib and she&amp;#8217;s throwing PVC&amp;#8217;s left and right. The medic&amp;#8217;s face tells me it&amp;#8217;s time to go and quickly. We calmly put her in the stair chair and get her out to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t know what happened after she left my care, but I&amp;#8217;d like to think that this time I made the right call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“Trauma” – my comment from the Happy Medic</title>
      <link>/p78/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2009 02:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p78/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Happy Medic &lt;a href=&#34;http://happymedic.com/2009/10/30/you-make-the-call-nbcs-trauma/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;recently asked his readers&lt;/a&gt; if they thought cancelling &amp;#8220;Trauma&amp;#8221; (my new favourite show [whimper]) was a good thing. You might be able to tell from the tone of my post, but I think the EMS community was largely ignorant in so quickly judging the show. If you only watched the pilot, said that it &amp;#8220;sucked&amp;#8221; and never tuned in again, you&amp;#8217;re a fool and I hope you put more effort into other parts of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It had a rough start, but I liked the direction it was heading. I found myself cringing less and less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I seem to have a different perspective on the show than most of my friends and co-workers You see. they&amp;#8217;re all bio and exercise science majors who are EMTs hoping to get into Med School or Nursing school, and I am a Theatre major who discovered EMS too late in a college career to change majors, and will be headed to Paramedic school after I finish my undergrad this year to pursue what I&amp;#8217;ve found that I truly love. My entire college career has focused on critiquing performance and media; so let me share a few unorganised thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like Trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was starting to see parts of my different partners in each of the characters. They also saw me in some of the characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The humour was getting better. A lot better. I remember the first time I thought they nailed &amp;#8220;on-scene humour&amp;#8221;, that the show might succeed or that as a community we might warm up to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think most EMS types were critical of it because it was different from what they were expecting. Just because it&amp;#8217;s not what you wanted doesn&amp;#8217;t make it &amp;#8220;bad.&amp;#8221; We readily recognise that foreign films may be good, just not our bag of crisps. Why can&amp;#8217;t we be so accepting of TV? Because it&amp;#8217;s not &amp;#8220;high art&amp;#8221; like film? The intent of the series was to entertain. A *byproduct* of that is to create awareness and raise questions. Most of us wanted a documentary. But guess what? The public doesn&amp;#8217;t want a documentary &amp;#8211; that&amp;#8217;s already been done in the late 90s on TLC (and yes I still watch those re-runs). Docs have been done &amp;#8211; and they&amp;#8217;re good but they&amp;#8217;re short running and don&amp;#8217;t make much money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The show does, however, have elements of a Doc. It&amp;#8217;s putting focus on a marginalised group. Luckily it wasn&amp;#8217;t shot like a doc or a news reel. People might have thought this actually 100% real to what we do. But guess what? TV viewers suspend their disbelief because they know it&amp;#8217;s a TV show. I doubt most people will be watching us code a family member, demanding to know why we aren&amp;#8217;t shocking the patient in asystole. Their memory of the events probably will resemble the way it&amp;#8217;s portrayed on Trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all complain that EMS is under-recognised and does not have a unified voice for change. Where do you expect that recognition to come from? Trauma generally put us in a good light &amp;#8211; shocking asystole and HEMS abuse aside. That raises awareness and creates the *opportunity* for dialogue. I think cancelling the show has closed a door for the EMS community. People could have started asking a lot of questions about us &amp;#8211; questions we could have answered. Instead of actualyl educating we said &amp;#8220;that&amp;#8217;s a dumb question.&amp;#8221; There&amp;#8217;s no faster way to turn off a student to a subject than communicating that. We were quick to judge, and rather than reach out a hand to lift up, we wished it to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I completely agree with the first comment here. Where do you think the writers and producers got these notions? Who else do we have to blame for misconceptions about our industry? If we want to create a positive imagine and change things for the better (EMS 2.0?) then we need to support exposure opportunities like Trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working for a volunteer EMS agency, I&amp;#8217;m acutely aware that things aren&amp;#8217;t always that action packed. And my maybe my &amp;#8220;young pup&amp;#8221; nature gets me excited for these intense traumas, MCIs, and other insanity on a weekly basis. Maybe the older guys are jaded enough to just think that it&amp;#8217;s stupid. I&amp;#8217;m with HM though &amp;#8211; somewhere someone watched this and decided to take that EMT-B class at their community college. Someone remembered that &amp;#8220;cool calls&amp;#8221; happen once in a while. Someone remembered when the Paramedics came and helped their [family member] with their [nature of illness or mechanism of injury] and how brave and skilled they were. And you know what? They probably remember is being just as intense as Trauma shows it &amp;#8211; even if it was &amp;#8220;just another diabetic.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To *us* it&amp;#8217;s a 9-5, and we stay calm because &amp;#8220;it&amp;#8217;s not my emergency.&amp;#8221; Well guess what? It&amp;#8217;s theirs. Every episode of Trauma was the most intense call ever, because that&amp;#8217;s the public&amp;#8217;s interaction with us &amp;#8211; and that&amp;#8217;s who the show was written for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that I think a valuable opportunity is leaving us, and that as a jaded community we blew it. A lot of good could have come from it. We only have ourselves to blame for the perception the media and the public have of us. When we want to communicate with the public we need to remember that they&amp;#8217;re different from us &amp;#8211; they aren&amp;#8217;t in &amp;#8220;the know.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goodbye, Paramedic Nancy Carnahan. I&amp;#8217;ll see you in my dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How not to replace a light bulb</title>
      <link>/p74/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2009 08:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p74/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An advantage of working in theatre is that you inevitably become very comfortable with working around electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  A disadvantage of working in theatre is that you inevitable become very comfortable with working around electricity.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  How &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to change a light bulb:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait until 2330.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  2. Go to WalMart. Marvel at the variety of light bulbs available since the last time you did some serious illumination shopping.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  2a. 20 Minutes Later: Hmmmm&amp;#8230;.if I buy CFL I can get higher output for less wattage? And they come colour corrected to 6k5? Sold.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  3. Return home. Remove glass cover from light fixture. Burn yourself because it was still hot.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  4. Leave is off and wait 30 minutes. Try again.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  5. Burn yourself on the light bulb because it was still hot. Wait 30 minutes and try again.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  6. Find that the light bulb is stuck. Ask Google how to get it out.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  7. Try &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.realsimple.com/home-organizing/home-improvement/remove-stuck-light-bulb-00000000002293/&#34;&gt;the duct tape method.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; No progress.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  8. Cover the light bulb with duct tape. Whack it with a screw driver to break it but keep the glass contained. Remember to put on wrap around eye-protection: BSI SCENE SAFETY!
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  9. Marvel in your brilliance as this is the only thing so far that has gone according to plan.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  10. Put pliers in socket and try to man handle what&amp;#8217;s left of the bulb&amp;#8217;s base. Get very small pieces of glass on the carpet.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  11. Make no progress.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  12. Ask Google about this situation.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  13. Go to the store and get a potato at 1am.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  14. Try &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ehow.com/how_2083998_remove-broken-lightbulb-potato.html&#34;&gt;the potato method&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#8221; Get lots of potato in the light socket. Make no progress.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  15. Unscrew the entire lighting fixture from the ceiling. Disconnect it from the power and pull it down.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  16. Go into the kitchen and use pliers to remove one small piece of the light bulb base at a time.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  17. Realise you forgot something where you were working before and go back for it. Absent mindedly flip light switch as you enter. When the shower of sparks from the exposed wires reminds you what you were just doing, frantically turn off light switch.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  18. Go back to kitchen. Finally remove remains of the light bulb. Wipe out potato with a bleach wipe.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  19. Reinstall light fixture. Drop wirenut.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  20. Spend 5 minutes on your hands and kness (in the broken glass) searching for the wirenut. In the dark.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  21. Find wirenut and finish re-wiring light fixture.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  22. Swear under your breath while trying to line up the holes for the screws to re-attach to the ceiling.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  23. Realise what the purpose is of the slots next to the holes.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  24. Cower as you flip on the switch to test for any wiring errors. Be rewarded with no electrical noises or sparks.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  25. Install CFLs and replace cover.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  26. Marvel at your awesomeness.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  27. Fetch the vacuum to cleanup the glass.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  28. Frantically turn off vacuum when you realise how loud it is at 2am.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  29. Use your flatmate&amp;#8217;s Roomba instead, because it&amp;#8217;s quite.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  30. Plug-in Roomba because it&amp;#8217;s batteries are dead.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  31. While Roomba charges, change the lock on your bedroom room like you&amp;#8217;d been meaning to all day.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  32. Start vacuuming with Roomba.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  32a. Learn to compensate for Roomba&amp;#8217;s inability to turn left.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  33. Half-way through, plug Roomba back in to charge and start blog post.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  34. Finish Vacuuming with Roomba.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  35. Proof and publish blog post.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tale of two patients</title>
      <link>/p67/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2009 05:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p67/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently responded to two different patients with the same complaint: shortness of breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Patient #1
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  As soon as we walked in the door she filled our ears with tales about how &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;ve been short of breath for a few days but today was worse and my blood pressure is all over the place when I gain or lose weight and right now I&amp;#8217;m heavier so it&amp;#8217;s higher and there&amp;#8217;s some tightness in my chest and which hospital am I going to and can my significant other come and what about my cat.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Verdict: Not sick.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Patient #2
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  As I walk in the door I can see the long tube for her supplemental oxygen snaking its way down the hall to her small bedroom. As I walk past the kitchen a hissing catches my attention: an oxygen concentrator running. The bedroom is equipped with a recliner, TV, and walker. She doesn&amp;#8217;t get around that easily. I can hear her gasping for air from the doorway. She says nothing, she can&amp;#8217;t, but the panic in her eyes tells me all I need to know. Her name was only a couple syllables, but that was too much to get out in a single breath. The normal light-hearted atmosphere we bring to calm a patient is gone. I do as I&amp;#8217;m told to assist in stabilising her before we whisk her off to hospital. In my robot mode of getting a d-stick, I unintentionally make eye contact with her as she attempts to sputter out a few syllables. She wants me to wipe her bloody nose &amp;#8211; the oxygen we put her on has dried her out. I clean her up and try to make her comfortable, asking for a humidifier. While I&amp;#8217;m doing this the medics are running a 12-lead and making a pin cushion of her arms trying to get a line. I&amp;#8217;m asked to bring in the gurney. As I cross the room my mind has a moment to wander. I look around and see pictures of children and grandchildren. She isn&amp;#8217;t in any of the portraits. Home blood pressure monitor. Caregiver says something about physical therapy earlier. She&amp;#8217;s been clearly been sick for a long time. This is someone&amp;#8217;s family member, and my heart pangs for a brief second as I realise these could be some of her last moments on Earth, shared only with me and 4 firemen. These thought&amp;#8217;s, while humanising, are ultimately unhelpful to providing emergent patient care. Engage reptilian brain: rescue doors open, trolley release, pull, drop legs, in front door, re-orient in the kitchen so it&amp;#8217;s facing the right way when I get to the bed, down hall, in bedroom. Use the sheet she&amp;#8217;s on to get her over. 1-2-3. Back to the rescue. Load and Go.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Verdict: Sick.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Epilogue:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  It never ceases to amaze me how readily people who &lt;strong&gt;don&amp;#8217;t&lt;/strong&gt; need ambulance services will call 9-1-1, but those who truly need them seem to wait until it&amp;#8217;s almost too late.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Patient 2 is part of a dying breed (literally) &amp;#8211; an older generation with a little something called self-reliance. They don&amp;#8217;t want to be a bother. They just want to have their peace. I respect and applaud them for that, especially when put in contrast to today&amp;#8217;s attitude of entitlement.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Talk to your grandparents if they&amp;#8217;re still around. You&amp;#8217;ll learn things too valuable to ever be committed to any book: teaching that transcend both language and generations.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In other news</title>
      <link>/p65/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2009 22:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p65/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two fun patient encounters today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 1 &amp;#8211;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cute girl: [runs up] can I get a Tylenol?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: Sure I just need your number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CG: Oh! [giggle] 999-555-1212&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: um, I meant your runner bib number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CG: [clearly disappointed] oh&amp;#8230; um [blush]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guy standing with girl the entire exchange: [grunt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 2 &amp;#8211;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: Is there any chance you&amp;#8217;re pregnant?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Girl with abdo pain: pfft&amp;#8230; I wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marathon Standby</title>
      <link>/p63/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2009 17:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p63/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To: anyone who wants to run a marathon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From: any medically oriented person&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Re: marathon training&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have an existing medical condition and a physician has told you not to run, a marathon counts as running. So don&amp;#8217;t do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and before you do 26.2 miles, best you do a few laps around the block &amp;#8211; hopefully more than 24 hours in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS nipples are not meant to bleed. And remember, other people have touched the Vaseline before you and will continue to after you. And yes, they put it in the same places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shiney!</title>
      <link>/p54/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2009 04:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p54/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I make a reasonable ammount of money. I used to have a blackberry, but the more I tried to use the internet the more annoyed I got with its limitations. So yesterday I took the plunge and went to the Apple store. I had to wait in line for an hour. I plunked down my $199 and walked out, and I don&amp;#8217;t think I&amp;#8217;ve put it down much since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does so many cool things to help me remain connected, feed my ADD, and just have fun. I don&amp;#8217;t think it will improve my patient care, except for a couple cool pharmacology applications, but it does keep me a little distracted. And I can&amp;#8217;t remember the last time I bought something for myself &amp;#8211; so why not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I can post to my blog from it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hope for the Future</title>
      <link>/p50/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2009 03:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p50/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/image55.gif&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/image55.gif?w=130&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often look at &amp;#8220;kids today&amp;#8221; and worry about what the world is coming to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably don&amp;#8217;t know it, but the image above is an illustration of a statue in Gilwell park, England that depicts &amp;#8220;the ideal Boy Scout.&amp;#8221; It was the basis for the apperance of young Indian Jones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last week I had the opportunity to spend the week watching 120 boys become young men. Every summer I volunteer at a scout camp. This isn&amp;#8217;t regular summer camp &amp;#8211; it&amp;#8217;s more like Boy Scout boot camp. The training programme is called National Youth Leadership Training or NYLT. I originally went through the programme in 1999 when it was called Junior Leader Training. I&amp;#8217;ve been on staff ever since; this last week marked my 10th year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005 the transition was made from JLT to NYLT curriculum. A lot of the camp traditions I&amp;#8217;d come to love we&amp;#8217;re yanked. One of them was a large pioneering project. The old course had scouts build a bridge across a cove as a sort of &amp;#8220;final&amp;#8221; for the week. It was epic. It made them proud, and it was a big accomplishment. After the first year of NYLT, we adjusted the schedule to accommodate a new pioneering project. It&amp;#8217;s taken a long time, but the programe has finally gotten close to its former glory. This year was the first time since 2004 that the kids have completed the pioneering project without staff intervention &amp;#8211; i.e. the first time since NYLT was implemented that they have been able to do what every JLT course has for the last 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so moved when they completed the project that I actually wept a little. These boys had gone from a group of complete strangers to a cohesive, productive group in just a few short days. They were able to organise themselves and build this fairly impressive structure. Who knows what they will be able to do with the future. Who knows what they will be able to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That night at troop assembly, I looked over them &amp;#8211; rag tag group of smelly 13-14 year old boys. Normally I might stop my assessment at that &amp;#8211; but in that moment I saw something else. I saw possibilities in every single one of them. Endless possibilities they could achieve if they put their minds to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was humbled to be a part of an early experience in their life that hopefully taught them something about who and what they are, and who and what they can be. They&amp;#8217;ve been home from camp for maybe two days now, and probably have already forgotten my name &amp;#8211; but I can still hold my head high knowing that I helped leave an impression on them for life. That I&amp;#8217;ve made the world just a little bit better by prodding an adolescent knuckle-head boy in the right direction. I feel so humble to have been a part of something so potentially life changing and great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Underwhelmed</title>
      <link>/p45/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2009 19:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p45/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold;&#34;&gt;warning&lt;/span&gt;: mixed theatre/film and EMS content ahead
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/img00005.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/img00005.jpg?w=225&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday I went to the &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;ct=res&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Flevelzeromovie.com%2F2009%2F04%2F10%2Flevel-zero-movie-trailer%2F&amp;amp;ei=NAQXSszPFY6UswOYme3ZCA&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNHeDBuahQHWLFk1kJElDMA2JKtoAw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Level Zero&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; premiere. From the trailer, it appears to be a fast paced, for-EMS-by-EMS documentary of work in Alameda County. That wasn&amp;#8217;t quite the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film is actually a 20 minute short only loosely associated with doc form. We loosely follow a couple EMTs and Medics through a fictitious busy day. The film consists of interviewing featured EMS providers about why they love EMS, how they got into it, etc., interspersed with some fictional depictions of real EMS work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When thinking about a film, it&amp;#8217;s important to consider the intent or the purpose. This film was made as a kick-off for EMS week. The premiere party (another subject of itself) was a &lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;party&lt;/span&gt;. This film is designed for EMS personnel, by EMS personnel to re-affirm &lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;their&lt;/span&gt; faith in the profession and why they do what they do. Unfortunately, I don&amp;#8217;t think the film had a broad enough appeal to interest people outside the region. Half the thrill of the premiere was seeing people you know on a big screen. So was the film successful in achieving its objective? I think so. Is it what I wanted it to be? No. Can I fault it for that? No, because I had false expectations. What I want would be better achieved by TLC or the group that produced &lt;a href=&#34;http://abc.go.com/specials/hopkins/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hopkins&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now&amp;#8230; the premiere party itself was more than I would have expected. Like I said about the film, this entire premiere event was a celebration of EMS providers about what we do. It was a fine night by all accounts &amp;#8211; but methinks there was too much ETOH. Every ticket to the premiere included &lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;font-weight:bold;&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; drink tickets. The event opened doors at 1830, and the film didn&amp;#8217;t screen until 2130. Some people were genuinely plastered by the time the film rolled. This was especially apparent in the Q&amp;amp;A after. To me, it was just a bit embarrassing. I know we&amp;#8217;re all &amp;#8220;among friends&amp;#8221; and whatnot, but I still don&amp;#8217;t think it was appropriate behaviour. When people know you&amp;#8217;re an EMT/Paramedic/Firefighter, there is a certain image you need to uphold. If you&amp;#8217;re in a bar off duty, out of uniform, and no one is the wiser, do what you like. However, if you&amp;#8217;re in a large group of people that are all assumed to be First Responders, you have a responsibility to maintain that image of honour and pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, now understanding the intent of the event and the film &amp;#8211; that it was faith affirming for those in the profession &amp;#8211; I can say it was a success. I am personally, though, disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/494505435792145067-4691745377047164866?l=nerdymedic.blogspot.com&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Almost Helpful</title>
      <link>/p43/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2009 00:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p43/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/img00007.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/img00007.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night it was unseasonably cold, so I was wearing my reflective EMS jacket because it&amp;#8217;s warm and cozy. I was sitting at Starbucks with a friend talking about &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_0&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-corrected&#34;&gt;health care&lt;/span&gt; reform &amp;#8211; which she&amp;#8217;s actually &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_1&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-corrected&#34;&gt;involved&lt;/span&gt; with in her job at the House in DC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;#8217;t see a thing in this crappy picture &amp;#8211; thanks &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_2&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;BlackBerry&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8211; but it was an &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_3&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;MVA&lt;/span&gt; involving 4 cars and as many patients. It happened right in front of me. As soon as it happened, I ran into the intersection and started checking on the occupants of the vehicles. Only one car had its airbags deployed. Everyone denied injury. Dang it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An officer arrived quickly, and I advised him that airbags had deployed in one vehicle but that no one was seriously injury and that Fire and EMS could probably downgrade their response from Code3. I knew we were two blocks from the closest Fire station and three blocks from the closest ambulance post. Lights and sirens wouldn&amp;#8217;t have really improved the response time &amp;#8211; but alas, I think the people demand it. A fire engine and ambulance came flying in, lights and sirens blazing in all the glory that I don&amp;#8217;t get to have. Having made no difference, I sulked back to Starbucks to tend to my caramel apple cider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time the Big Ambulance Company arrived on scene, Fire had already started cleanup of the fluids leaking from the mini-van that was hit head on. The ambulance medic actually convinced one of the people &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_4&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-corrected&#34;&gt;involved&lt;/span&gt; in the accident to get in the back of the rig. They probably pulled the old &amp;#8220;an &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_5&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-corrected&#34;&gt;ambulance&lt;/span&gt; ride is cheaper than a funeral&amp;#8221; gag. I&amp;#8217;ll bet they even called it a trauma activation *rolls eyes*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, I guess it&amp;#8217;s good no one was hurt because I didn&amp;#8217;t have any actual kit with me besides gloves. Maybe an arrest? Bystander CPR makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah&amp;#8230;no. None for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not an adrenaline junky…no…not me</title>
      <link>/p41/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2009 08:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight I went indoor skydiving &amp;#8211; Oh. my. wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;130mph wind is a lot. You get to fly. For reals. I had to seriously concentrate to keep my posture, and my back is a little sore, but I&amp;#8217;ll definitely go again. Nursing Programme Partner insists that we go after her sister&amp;#8217;s wedding reception later this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, these are sensations a flight medic/nurse probably never wants to experience outside of a plexi-glass tube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So do I love EMS or am I an adrenaline junky? I might have a chance to work at Google this summer doing my usual sound/technical theatre stuff. Regular hours, decent pay, awesome cafeteria, and cute girls. But I don&amp;#8217;t think I would be happy. I want to be in the streets scraping people off the side-walks and taking care of them. I want the glory or lights and sirens. Given the choice of working for Google and taking 911 calls, I would jump on the ambulance in a second, even if it meant less pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think maybe the reason I liked doing theatre so much was because it was sort of part-time. Work a week here and then have a month off. Work 3 on 3 off. Work 4 on 7 off &amp;#8211; or however it sorts out. EMS shift work would be similar&amp;#8230; I could handle having 4 days off a week and doing &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;#8217;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I want to be when I grow up? What do I want to be this summer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prized possessions</title>
      <link>/p39/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2009 01:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/lfhp.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/lfhp.jpg?w=150&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this was in blue it would be my LifeFlight sweater. It&amp;#8217;s one of my most prised possessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was too hot to wear it today walking between my seminar and the train station. I was actually annoyed by this &amp;#8211; not because I had to carry my coat, but because I couldn&amp;#8217;t &lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;wear&lt;/span&gt; this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does that say about me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ride home</title>
      <link>/p37/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2009 01:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve spent the entire day at a high-end professional speaker manufacturer learning about sound system measurement, alignment, and tuning. There was a time when I would have really enjoyed this. Instead I find it hard to concentrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the train ride home I&amp;#8217;m listening to EMS CE lecture podcasts. I&amp;#8217;m reading EMS blogs. I&amp;#8217;m writing in my blog about how much I love EMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;#8217;s the hot girl sitting next to me, but she&amp;#8217;s wearing a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claddagh_ring&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;claddagh ring&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; crown out. Damn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is what I choose to do in my spare time, why don&amp;#8217;t I just go in head first? What am I afraid of &amp;#8211; actually enjoying what I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CCFD</title>
      <link>/p36/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2009 21:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While visiting Las Vegas I had the opportunity to do a ride along with the Clark County Fire Department. Their agency responds to about 120,000 9-1-1 calls per year. Last year my agency was just shy of 600. CCFD is the proud home of Station 18 &amp;#8211; &amp;#8220;the pride of the strip&amp;#8221; &amp;#8211; which has the honour of being the busiest firehouse in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All it took was a quick call to Fire Administration and asking for the EMS coordinator, who after a brief conversation directed me to the EMS supervisor to find the actual station I would be posted at for the day. I wound up at station 23 in the heart of the ghetto of North Las Vegas. I was excited for the onslaught of crime, grime, and blood that awaited me as an overanxious newer EMT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reported at 0900. We got our first call shortly after my arrival for a woman &amp;#8220;feeling sick.&amp;#8221; Code 1 alpha response. Snooze. I think I&amp;#8217;ve been on that call with &lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; agency. The medic let me start doing a full patient evaluation, but eventually cut me off when the transport ambulance arrived. &amp;#8220;Okay, so what hospital do you want to go to?&amp;#8221; One of the unique things about a pay for transport system is that everyone &amp;#8220;should&amp;#8221; go to the hospital. The cost of transport is not figured into what is or is not in the patient&amp;#8217;s best interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engine then went on a call for 23 yof with abdominal pain. WTF ru serious? I thought I left the world of volunteer EMS? The captain bet the engineer on the rescue a drink that the patient would be at least 300 pounds. Apparently she was not, and the captain sent a rookie to go pay the debt in fire service gold: mountain dew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third call was back pain coded as a charlie with code 3 response. &amp;#8220;Must be some really bad back pain.&amp;#8221; The guy has an irregular heart rhythm that was a fun ECG to look at. The transport medic got very excited about the degree of the block and the conduction ratio, the non conducted beats, etc. While I kept it to myself, I understood (and could see) everything he was talking about. The fire medic, however, made fun of transport medic. I could almost hear him say &amp;#8220;nerd alert&amp;#8221; under his breath. Back at the station the captain remarked, &amp;#8220;it&amp;#8217;s not really that hard. You ask if you want to go to the hospital and put them on oxygen. Start an IV if they&amp;#8217;re &lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;actually&lt;/span&gt; sick. The end.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind these were the only calls that occurred between 0900 and about 1700. I was allowed to stay at the station until 2200. The crew apologised that their clientele was disappointing today. I responded that I understood how that always seemed to work with ride-alongs. Depressed and exhausted, I was ready to give up and leave around 2100, but got into a conversation with the engine medic about a house he was building. At 2155, as I was gathering my things, the whole station was paged for a multiple shooting. 4 victims. One in the chest. Police report code 4 to enter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally my job is to grab the airway bag. When we arrive, the medic yells back, &amp;#8220;just get a backboard; we&amp;#8217;re getting out of here.&amp;#8221; The victim had a single superficial wound near his right clavicle. PD reported that they thought it was likely a ricochet. &amp;#8220;Hablas ingles?&amp;#8221; No, of course not, but AOx4 &amp;#8211; we think. Occlusive dressing on, even though it wasn&amp;#8217;t sucking let alone bleeding much. NRB on. Collar on. Roll. Back clear. Backboard under. Straps on. Gurney. Lift. Headbed. Into transport ambulance. Code 3. Go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In transport I was attaching leads, spiking IV bags, adjusting drip rates, checking breath sounds, and monitoring LOC and airway. Being an intermediate it was awesome to understand every detail of what the medics were both doing and saying. My assessments and interventions were productive. I was helping this guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the closest to being alive that I&amp;#8217;ve felt in a long time. And on top of it the transport medic was smokin&amp;#8217; hot. The call was so good, I thought I needed a cigarette after &amp;#8211; and I don&amp;#8217;t smoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, that good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that call, I had no doubt in my mind that I wanted to go to paramedic school. The longer I do theatre, the more bored I get with it. In the mean time it pays three times as well as any EMS job I could get, if I could get hired anywhere. However, this all occurs to me as I&amp;#8217;m sitting through a 4-day seminar for theatre-sound related training. At lunch I drifted off in a conversation when an ambulance went by. I&amp;#8217;m writing this post in class right now because I&amp;#8217;m fantasising about being back on the front lines, speeding around with lights and sirens blaring, making a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this isn&amp;#8217;t some fleeting infatuation. I need career true love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodies – The Exhibition</title>
      <link>/p35/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2009 03:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/bodies1.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/bodies1.gif?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I went to &amp;#8220;Bodies &amp;#8211; The Exhibition&amp;#8221; in Las Vegas at the the Luxor. Most people sort of glanced at things and stayed an arms length away form the cadavers. They seemed to be I got as close as I possibly could (inches) from the cadavers and read every word of every exhibit. At one point, wtih my face inches from an opened thoracic cavity, I muttered &amp;#8220;these don&amp;#8217;t smell like cadavers&amp;#8221; under my breath and received strange glances from the other people in the hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human body is an amazingly complex and beautiful machine. So many things happen in so many places at so many levels. So many levels of complexity and function drill down perfectly in seamless functions like ballrom dance and playing musical instruments &amp;#8211; it&amp;#8217;s like the ideal ICS implimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;#8217;t terribly impressed with the detail of the exhibition. There wasn&amp;#8217;t a whole lot I didn&amp;#8217;t know already &amp;#8211; which isn&amp;#8217;t saying much. It was still, however, a very educational experience. It&amp;#8217;s one thing to know how things are hooked up; it&amp;#8217;s another to actually see them that way. Sitting on front of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the cadaver lab at my university is cooler though. You can actually handle parts and pieces and look at them in any orientation you want. Being stuck behind plexiglass was frustrating. I wanted a pair of gloves, a spay bottle, and a probe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the spiritual side of things, the exhibit really took my eyes to the heavens. The human body is truly beautiful. Every breath we take and every beat of our heart is a miracle. Indeed all things indicate there is a God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a side note, winner for best comment in the guest book of the walkout area was: &amp;#8220;Our muscles look like turkey meat. I&amp;#8217;m never eating turkey again.&amp;#8221; Heh. I have a sudden graving for wings&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“Sirens of TI” as an example of the new genre of 21st century melodrama</title>
      <link>/p31/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2009 18:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold;&#34;&gt;warning: theatre content&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/sirens_tre00384_720x503.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/sirens_tre00384_720x503.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although most people may see the &amp;#8220;Sirens of TI&amp;#8221; show at Treasure Island as &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_0&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;contentless&lt;/span&gt; spectacle, there&amp;#8217;s much more to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The melodrama of the 20&lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_1&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;th&lt;/span&gt; century featured polarised morality and spectacle. &amp;#8220;Sirens,&amp;#8221; however, is 21st century melodrama. One of the biggest changes in drama for the last two decades is the confusion of morality. Melodrama used to be clear cut good v. bad. There was the white hat hero and the black mustache tie-you-to-the-train-tracks bad villain. Both were easily identifiable and there was nothing in between. Today&amp;#8217;s melodrama is an exploration of moral issues. What makes us good or bad? Is it what we do or why we do it? Think about this before you answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/jack-bauer.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://wp.docker.localhost:8000/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/jack-bauer.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all agree that Jack Bauer is a hero. Consider his actions. A lot of people consider what he does &amp;#8220;wrong,&amp;#8221; but we stand up and cheer for his because of his reasons for doing it. He frequently will sacrifice his own moral character for the great good of the safety of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stands in contrast to &amp;#8220;the grotesque&amp;#8221; movement of the romantic period. The romantic period started blending different elements of characters. The characters themselves were, however, still very distinct and readily identifiable. In the 21st century, we don&amp;#8217;t know who is who.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nerdymedic.files.wordpress.com/2009/04/26vegascheap4.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://nerdymedic.files.wordpress.com/2009/04/26vegascheap4.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Sirens&amp;#8221; is no different. There are pirates and sirens. Criminals (particularly poignant given recent events) and mythical sex goddesses. Ironically, the Siren&amp;#8217;s ship is white &amp;#8211; normally symbolic of purity. The visual design of the pirate&amp;#8217;s vessel is clearly influenced by a Peter Pan &amp;#8220;lost boys&amp;#8221; style. The Sirens seduce the Pirates. Clearly in this performance the Pirates are the victims &amp;#8211; &amp;#8220;lost boys&amp;#8221; who are helpless to the seduction of women. This is also a sexual role reversal from what was portrayed just 20 years ago. Vampire literature (and other similarly sexual &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_2&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-corrected&#34;&gt;story lines&lt;/span&gt;) has always shown men as the &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_3&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-corrected&#34;&gt;aggressor&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8211; but that&amp;#8217;s changed now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who is good? Who is evil? Why are we motivated to do thing? What is the true measure of our character? The Pirates, ironically are standing up their honour. The Sirens are seeking &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_4&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-corrected&#34;&gt;purely&lt;/span&gt; after carnal desire. In the end the Sirens win. What is the show teaching? Immediate gratification is good. Impulse control is bad. Welcome to Vegas. We&amp;#8217;re here to help you with that &amp;#8211; for a small fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nerdymedic.files.wordpress.com/2009/04/sirens_of_ti_1.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://nerdymedic.files.wordpress.com/2009/04/sirens_of_ti_1.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things, though, will never change. The melodrama of the 18&lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_5&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;th&lt;/span&gt; and 19&lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_6&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;th&lt;/span&gt; centuries featured spectacle. It was all about putting on a big show &amp;#8211; bigger, better, louder. Epic. The 19&lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_7&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;th&lt;/span&gt; century featured a sub-genre called &amp;#8220;firefighter melodrama&amp;#8221; that was popular because they got to burn things on stage. The same is true with &amp;#8220;Sirens.&amp;#8221; As they&amp;#8217;ve proven on &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_8&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;Mythbusters&lt;/span&gt;, it&amp;#8217;s always better to end with a bang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the bottom line is that &amp;#8220;Sirens of TI&amp;#8221; has been written in the melodramatic style because it&amp;#8217;s historically about escapism &amp;#8211; and guess what Vegas is trying to create. &amp;#8220;What happens in Vegas stays in Vegas.&amp;#8221; &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_9&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;Las&lt;/span&gt;Vegas itself is performance. It&amp;#8217;s all a show. People come here to fulfill the same escapist desire. It&amp;#8217;s carnal. It&amp;#8217;s deeply rooted, and it a lot ways it&amp;#8217;s sad that people have no greater source of joy in their life. I think it&amp;#8217;s sad the the closest many people come to &amp;#8220;being alive&amp;#8221; is being to close to something that is completely (and openly) contrived in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Said tonight in EMT I/85 class</title>
      <link>/p25/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2009 03:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m trying to intubate our code manikin on the floor; against the wall. I&amp;#8217;m really struggling to see anything. My arm is shaking. I&amp;#8217;m sweating. This is a lot harder than when it&amp;#8217;s on the gurney or a well-lit table at waist level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPP is visiting class tonight. She starts poking and prodding my neck &amp;#8211; while I&amp;#8217;m riding this bull of a manakin at the airway rodeo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Stop palpating my jugular!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 minutes of FAIL</title>
      <link>/p22/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2009 05:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INT. &amp;#8212; NERD ALERT&amp;#8217;S APARTMENT. MID-DAY.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FLATMATE 1 walks in, leans over FLATMATE 2 to get his laptop, knocks daiquiri off coffee table on to carpet. Que EVERYONE scrambling to clean it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the process FLATMATE 1 throws a door open to get to the rags. At this point it&amp;#8217;s discovered that for the past 8 months this door &amp;#8211; when fully opened &amp;#8211; could nail the 42&amp;#8243; flat-screen HDTV. It does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Que NA screaming like he&amp;#8217;s just seen a puppy get assassinated. The centre speaker of the surround system is knocked into the wall behind the TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not 30 seconds after the ordeal NA swigs his root beer, forgetting it was full. The foam fizzes up and quickly overwhelms his ability to keep it in his cheeks, spraying across the floor as he sprints for the sink. He laughs so hard it comes out of every orifice of his face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and, scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Said on AIM today</title>
      <link>/p19/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2009 18:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;NPP: *growl*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPP: just growling about pay. i&amp;#8217;m not allowed to growl prn?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: LOL&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History of Present Relationship</title>
      <link>/p18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2009 07:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When it comes time in a relationship to &amp;#8220;define the relationship&amp;#8221; or &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_0&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;DTR&lt;/span&gt;, you may find it useful to remember to use &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_1&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;OPQRST&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onset &amp;#8211; How did this start? Did you start liking me suddenly? Slowly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provokes &amp;#8211; Does anything I do make you like me more or less? Has it been getting better or worse lately?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quality &amp;#8211; If you had to describe how you like me in one word, what would it be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radiates &amp;#8211; Can you point to where I seem to affect you? Just your heart?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Severity &amp;#8211; If you had to rate our relationship on a scale of 1 to 10&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time &amp;#8211; When exactly did this come about? Is this the first time you&amp;#8217;ve liked someone this way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There. Now you have a history of the present relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disappointment</title>
      <link>/p17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2009 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My posts are not in the order they necessarily occur(ed) in. Since I&amp;#8217;ll likely be posting about previous events for a while, they&amp;#8217;re in the order that they cross my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve put my heart and soul into band-aid brigade EMS here in my little town. In two semester I&amp;#8217;ve put in over 400 hours of documented shift time (more than twice what&amp;#8217;s required), a lot of other time, cut class to go to CME opportunities, listened to hundreds of hours of medical podcasts, and generally done everything I can to provider better patient care and uplift and educate the people I run with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when they invited people to apply for supervisor positions next year, I was excited. I wanted more opportunities to educate, challenge, and uplift people in my service. I&amp;#8217;ve spent almost a decade as an active staff member in Boy Scout leadership camps. I&amp;#8217;m an experienced teacher. I don&amp;#8217;t think you could ask for someone more passionate or qualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my interview I mentioned my desire to educate and reform. Fearless Leader (our EMS director) asked exactly what I meant. So I quickly threw out a couple suggestions about doing call reviews during our weekly meetings, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I didn&amp;#8217;t get the position. Who did? A bunch of people that do the bare minimum. Also, imagine my surprise in class last week when Fearless Leader announces that we will be doing &amp;#8220;grand rounds&amp;#8221; (a gussied up word for call reviews) form time to time. Great. He&amp;#8217;s also mentioned implementing some of the other ideas I brought up in my interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had such great ideas, why not put me in a position to execute them? Why not call me a training officer? Honestly I feel a little betrayed or undercut. Is it wrong to feel that way? Is it wrong to almost resent the people who did get it because I feel significantly more qualified?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger question is: does it matter? The answer to that is probably not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>*snort*</title>
      <link>/p11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2009 03:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;NPP is sitting with me at work right now &amp;#8211; the job I actually get paid to do (theatre), not the one I actually like (ems) &amp;#8211; watching a comedy show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPP: Can I be nerdy for just a sec?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA: Sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPP: My sternocleidomastoid muscle is sore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &amp;lt;3 you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“oops”</title>
      <link>/p9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2009 02:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here on the band-aid brigade we like to remember mistakes that could have had bad outcomes, but didn&amp;#8217;t. We call this an &amp;#8220;oops&amp;#8221; list. My favourite oops happened this semester. I was on shift with Nursing Programme Partner, a third band-aid brigader, and a couple ride alongs from the EMT-Basic class. A full house in our EMS closet, er office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get paged for &amp;#8220;male experiencing chest pain, palpitations, and shortness of breath.&amp;#8221; City Fire is dispatched simultaneously per the EMD card. We sprint out to the gutless wonder, about 150 metres from our office. NPP is driving. I&amp;#8217;m riding shotgun to run the lights and air-horn. I yell back to the ride alongs &amp;#8220;let&amp;#8217;s go, let&amp;#8217;s go.&amp;#8221; NPP starts to peel out of the driveway, thinking I was talking to her. While one of the ride alongs is still getting in the van. Nearly tumbling the ground as they try to step on the now moving running board. F. Do we have multiple patients now? No. Ride along climbs in, adrenaline pumping at the appropriate level now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;Appendix A: the actual call&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual call could have been interesting. While a young male with chest pain screams &amp;#8220;anxiety&amp;#8221; to me, most young males aren&amp;#8217;t seeing a cardiologist and taking beta-blockers for a consistent disrhytmia and a family history of conduction disorders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HR 15o taken manually. 324mg ASA PO. O2 @ 15 lpm by NRB. City Fire calls and asks if we want them to come in code-3 &amp;#8211; &amp;#8220;uh, yeah&amp;#8221; I communicate to NPP with with the flick of an eyebrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The City Fire medics appear, clearly disappointed that their dinner/movie/Halo tourney was interrupted for this. I give my hand-off to the Medic, who has us put the pt on City Fire&amp;#8217;s monitor. Sinus tac. The Medic zeroes in quickly on a diagnosis of anxiety. But the pt wants to go to Level-2 Regional Medical Centre just down the street. I&amp;#8217;m pretty sure after they got him in the Rescue that they started 12&amp;#8217;s bilaterally just because he annoyed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really wish band-aid brigade could do some Intermediate interventions. It would help us rule out a lot of things City Fire has to come for. But if there&amp;#8217;s one thing I&amp;#8217;ve learned, it&amp;#8217;s that we aren&amp;#8217;t trusted. Case in point below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;Appendix B: playing hookie&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;I keep a high GPA. That&amp;#8217;s because I go to class. Consistently. But a couple weeks ago I played hookie. That&amp;#8217;s right &amp;#8211; I&amp;#8217;ve been in college for 5 years and this was the first time I consciously decided not to go to class. *le gasp*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simmer down. I went to an EMS conference with NPP. I learned more there than I would have in class anyway. We talked to some people with LifeFlight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does HEMS have such a visceral, romantic appeal? I think it&amp;#8217;s because it&amp;#8217;s the closest you can get to being a superhero &amp;#8211; actually flying in to save the day. The flight nurse we talked to offered as some posters that had their transport criteria and LZ protocols on them. We squealed with glee, taking copies for bedrooms (nerd alert), and one for the band-aid brigade office. The flight nurse informs us that this might actually come in handy. Although Level-2 Regional Medical Centre is two blocks away, &amp;#8220;in the event of an MCI,&amp;#8221; he informs us that he &amp;#8220;might be flying patients to other medical centres in the state.&amp;#8221; We ooh and ahh at the prospect, and take the HEMS poster back to our EMS director who happens to be at the conference with us. Our director (let&amp;#8217;s call him &amp;#8220;Fearless Leader&amp;#8221;) is generally a nice guy, but sometimes he&amp;#8217;s a little short with us. Especially via e-mail. The follow up conversation with our new &amp;#8220;toy&amp;#8221; (the poster) went something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA and NPP: FL, FL! Looks what we got! Now can land a helicopter if something terrible ever happens! Hoo-rah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FL: You guys realise you won&amp;#8217;t ever do that. The cops will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA and NPP: *whimper*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might as well have told us there was no Santa Clause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another (more serious) example of not being trusted. For any &amp;#8220;difficulty breathing&amp;#8221; dispatch, City Fire is dispatched simultaneously. Unfortunately, this encompasses every college aged girl who ever has a panic attack. And we can&amp;#8217;t tell City Fire to cancel and stay at the Station to finish their movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh well. One day I&amp;#8217;ll get to do real EMS and really help people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Band-aid Brigade</title>
      <link>/p8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2009 02:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I yearn for a decent call. When I hear the fire station closest to campus get paged for a medical, I start salivating like a wild animal. I see red. In my head I start running through ACLS trees, timing compressions, considering the fastest way to get across campus given the traffic patterns for the time of day. And then&amp;#8230; it&amp;#8217;s not on campus. Auto-ped&amp;#8230;two out of our response area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe City Fire will call for mutual aid&amp;#8230;.yeah right&amp;#8230;.they&amp;#8217;d call the next state over before that ever happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously? I know if you&amp;#8217;re riding a bike in this town you go to school here. You couldn&amp;#8217;t have gotten hurt on campus instead? FML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our tones go off moments later&amp;#8230;blood pressure spikes&amp;#8230;standby for medical&amp;#8230;adrenaline released&amp;#8230;.blood floods my legs&amp;#8230;ready to sprint to someone&amp;#8217;s aid. Dispatch keys up&amp;#8230;Sprained ankle. FML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someday I&amp;#8217;ll be a real EMS provider &amp;#8211; i.e., more than a buffer between the Fire Department and typical &lt;s&gt;idiocy&lt;/s&gt; BLS we respond to. I&amp;#8217;d like to really help someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fly in to save the day&amp;#8230; is that my dream? I don&amp;#8217;t know. But for now, I do what I can with the campus band-aid brigade, snatching you from the jaws of death in our gutless wonder from 0700 to 2300 most days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technical Theatre v. EMS</title>
      <link>/p7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2009 02:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I like to think that I keep a level head on a scene and do the best assessment I can do. I&amp;#8217;ve also noticed that EMTs and theatre technicians share the same of sense of humour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;Technical Theatre&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a live performance environment, you have one shot to get things right. Lives are not at stake, but there&amp;#8217;s enough money involved that people act like there are. On a Broadway show people are paying hundreds of dollars per seat. Missing one wireless microphone pickup could cost the performance big time. I strap thousands of dollars worth of equipment to performers that are going to sweat and dance with it. Sometimes the shows I work on are broadcast live &amp;#8211; lots of room for &amp;#8220;oops&amp;#8221; there. But, I don&amp;#8217;t let it bother me. No matter how high profile, a show is just a little indoor skit. Sometimes they&amp;#8217;re a little bigger, but when it comes down to it, you do the best you can, and it&amp;#8217;s all you can do. You&amp;#8217;d better be good at what you do so you can do it: fast, in the dark, under pressure, and perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;EMS&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;In an EMS in environment, you have one shot to get things right. Lives are often &lt;span style=&#34;font-style:italic;&#34;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; at stake, but medical care costs are enough that people act like they are. When it comes down to it, you do the best you can, and it&amp;#8217;s all you can do. You&amp;#8217;d better be good at what you do so you can do it: fast, in the dark, under pressure, and perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It really takes the same kind of person to do either, which is why it hasn&amp;#8217;t been a difficult transition for me. It&amp;#8217;s just a new skill set. So technical theatre and EMS &amp;#8211; not so different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dramatis Persona</title>
      <link>/p6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2009 01:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve ever read a play, you know that it usually begins with a cast of characters &amp;#8211; sometimes called a dramatis persona. I&amp;#8217;m going to introduce myself and some of the people in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold;&#34;&gt;Nursing Programme Partner&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8211; NPP is my main partner on EMS. We run more shifts together than anyone else. On a call, we can hand each other a piece of equipment before the other asks for it. We know what line of questioning we&amp;#8217;re going down. We can tell jokes with the exchange of a single glance. She&amp;#8217;s also in the nursing programme at my school. She&amp;#8217;s getting her BSN in hopes of one day working in HEMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold;&#34;&gt;Short Partner&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8211; SP is one of my favourite people. She&amp;#8217;s short, blonde, and loves to laugh. We laugh together. Sometimes too much. Sometimes inappropriately. She also wants to be a flight nurse, but is self-admittedly not super academic. She&amp;#8217;s planning on going to para school and bridging to an RN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold;&#34;&gt;FireFighter Partner&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8211; FFP is a more recent addition to my cast of friends. He hales from a rural area where he was a volunteer with the fire brigade. He&amp;#8217;s a great EMT, and having been on a variety of calls, always keeps a level head &amp;#8211; unlike most of us here who will knock down a baby to get to a sprained ankle call three seconds faster. FFP and I will be flatmates next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold;&#34;&gt;EMT Flatmate &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8211; Thrown together by chance this year, EF and I will be rooming together next year along with FFP. EF is a funny guy. He&amp;#8217;s currently dating SP, and holdes a crudge againt me for raping his arm with my second ever attempt at an IV start. Yeah, yeah&amp;#8230; so what if it&amp;#8217;s still bruised almost two weeks later&amp;#8230; I got flash. I got the other two that night on my first stick&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold;&#34;&gt;Nerd Alert&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8211; I&amp;#8217;m a theatre major, but I&amp;#8217;m also an EMT. I&amp;#8217;m planning on going to para school and bridging to an RN in hopes of getting into HEMS. Maybe. Or perhaps I&amp;#8217;ll go to PA school. I don&amp;#8217;t think I could handle being stuck in a hospital forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why am I a theatre major you ask? Well, for the last eight years of my life I&amp;#8217;ve been doing theatre professionally. I was good at it. So I pursued it in college and continued building my career. I&amp;#8217;ve done sound for Apple, Intel, Oracle, Cisco, Google, Sun Microsystems, Phyzer, The Rolling Stones, Metallica, Green Day, Rage Against the Machine, and the San Francisco Opera and Symphony, just to name a few. I&amp;#8217;ve turned down opportunities to go on national musical theatre tours, etc. I&amp;#8217;m good at what I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve also seen lots of people get pretty seriously hurt in professional theatre. I took my EMT-Basic class because I wanted to be better prepared for when things happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I liked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this when I was a handful of classes short of finishing my theatre degree. Having transferred between a couple colleges, I&amp;#8217;m already taking 6 years (and &amp;gt;170 semester credits) to finish my undergrad. So no change of major for me. I am, however, taking chemistry, anatomy, physiology, etc., so I can continue my medical ambitions. If I choose to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My pseudonym (Nerd Alert) is an official nickname from my EMT-Intermediate class. I&amp;#8217;m a theatre major, but I&amp;#8217;ve audited both anatomy and physiology. Why? I like knowing what I&amp;#8217;m doing for my patients and why it works. The problem with that? When people ask why this drug works for this, or why something is done this way, I answer it &amp;#8211; sometimes when even the instructor can&amp;#8217;t. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Student: So why can&amp;#8217;t you give &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_0&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;glucagon&lt;/span&gt; twice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instructor: Because it uses up all the sugar stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Student: From where? The blood sugar is already low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instructor: I don&amp;#8217;t know, it just uses them up and you can&amp;#8217;t give it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nerd Alert: &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_1&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;Glucagon&lt;/span&gt; is a hormone that stimulates &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_2&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;glycogenolysis&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8211; breaking down glycogen stores in the liver to be released in the blood stream. Once you&amp;#8217;ve used up the glycogen stores by giving &lt;span id=&#34;SPELLING_ERROR_3&#34; class=&#34;blsp-spelling-error&#34;&gt;glucagon&lt;/span&gt;, obviously you can&amp;#8217;t do it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instructor (in a playground sing-song): Nerd Alert! Nerd Alert! Nerd Alert!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m almost proud of that. Almost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
